<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mnemonica, or, The art of memory drained out of the pure fountains of art &amp; nature, digested into three books : also a physical treatise of cherishing natural memory, diligently collected out of divers learned mens writings / by John Willis.</title>
            <title>Mnemonica, sive, Reminiscendi ars. English. 1661</title>
            <author>Willis, John, d. 1628?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 216 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08250633</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08250633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41178</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66483)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41178)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1244:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mnemonica, or, The art of memory drained out of the pure fountains of art &amp; nature, digested into three books : also a physical treatise of cherishing natural memory, diligently collected out of divers learned mens writings / by John Willis.</title>
                  <title>Mnemonica, sive, Reminiscendi ars. English. 1661</title>
                  <author>Willis, John, d. 1628?</author>
                  <author>Sowerby, Leonard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 175 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Leonard Sowersby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated from the Latin by Leonard Sowersby.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Memory.</term>
               <term>Mnemonics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41178:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41178:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MNEMONICA;</hi> OR, THE Art of Memory, Drained out of the pure FOUNTAINS OF <hi>ART</hi> &amp; <hi>NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</hi> Digeſted into Three Books.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO,</hi> A Phyſical TREATISE of cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Natural Memory;</hi> diligently col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of divers Learned Mens WRITINGS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Willis</hi> Batchelour in Divinity.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Omne bonum Dei donum.</p>
               <p>Ut unaquaeque ars nobiliſſima ac diviniſſima fuit; ita ad mortalium cognitionem tardiſsimè per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cardanus.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and are to be ſold by <hi>Leonard Sowersby,</hi> at the Turn-ſtile, near New-market, in Lincolns-Inn fields, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41178:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41178:2"/>
            <head>To the Honorable <hi>William Pierrepont,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honored Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF Lines were capable of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affections, theſe would bluſh, they are ſo mean a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſo Illuſtrious and perſon; at leaſt conſcious of their Maſters preſumption, they would condole his unhappineſs, that had not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ability to accommodate ſome more worthy Fabrick to ſo fair a Frontiſpiece. The Original compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a learned hand, among ſome vulgar things and trifles, containeth very excellent and profitable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; I hope it hath not loſt its utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:41178:3"/>(though Grace) in Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honored Sir,</hi> I fear, good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are no ſufficient Plea for teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Enterpriſes, eſpecially the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker being privie to his own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections; Therefore like a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal acknowledging my vanity in ambitiouſly affecting things above my Sphere, I humbly re-implore your Honors pardon and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to be what I was before,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors moſt humble Servant</hi> Leonard Sowersby.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41178:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I hope Courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this my <hi>Art of Memory</hi> is ſo perfect and complete in all parts, that it will out-live the envy of <hi>Detractors;</hi> yet ſeeing like a new-born Infant, it doth now firſt preſent it ſelf to the world, let me in a word or two demonſtrate how agreeable this Art is, both to Reaſon, and the principles of Nature, that ſo I may recall, what the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of many hath long proſcribed. I do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well underſtand the whole Controverſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this Art, is principally referred to that part which is called <hi>Local:</hi> Therefore wholly omitting the other helps of <hi>Memory,</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the firſt and ſecond parts of this Book, I will onely inſiſt upon defence of this which is handled in the third Book, and will prove by moſt evident reaſons, it doth not ſo much vary from Art and natural uſe of <hi>Memory,</hi> as ignorant perſons prate.</p>
            <p>Firſt I acknowledge and willingly confeſs, that <hi>Writing</hi> is the ſureſt <hi>Guardian</hi> of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable things, far excelling all other Art of <hi>Memory;</hi> but a man cannot always commit
<pb facs="tcp:41178:4"/>to writing every thing he deſireth to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and muſt therefore neceſſarily ſometimes make uſe of other helps: As writing <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandums</hi> is worthily eſteemed the beſt way of <hi>Remembring;</hi> ſo that may rightly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the next place, which beareth greateſt affinity thereto. Now if men deal impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they will eaſily find, that the <hi>Art of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> by <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Idea's</hi> or <hi>Images,</hi> doth very nearly reſemble <hi>Writing.</hi> The <hi>Places</hi> in artificial <hi>Memory,</hi> are as it were <hi>Leavs;</hi> the <hi>Idea's, Letters;</hi> the diſtribution of them in <hi>Places</hi> repreſenteth <hi>Writing;</hi> laſtly, the repetition of them, <hi>Reading:</hi> which thing <hi>Cicero</hi> in his <hi>Partitions,</hi> but more copiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his ſecond Book <hi>De Oratore,</hi> doth ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly declare.</p>
            <p>Secondly, experience teacheth, that <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Idea's</hi> do much conduce to faithful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of things; particularly as to <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> their uſefulneſs doth hence appear, that if a Traveller obſerve any remarkable thing in a croſs-way, or ſome noted place of his journey, returning the ſame way, he doth not onely remember the place, but calleth to mind what ſoever he had ſeen there, though at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent removed. The ſame thing often happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in <hi>Repetition</hi> of <hi>Idea's;</hi> for the mind as it were walking through the ſame <hi>Places,</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:41178:4"/>which formerly it had diſpoſed <hi>Idea's,</hi> and carefully marſhalled them in order, with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of peruſal, by occaſion of the <hi>Places,</hi> is much aſſiſted in recalling <hi>Idea's</hi> to mind there placed: So Printers by Diſtrribution of their Letters into ſeveral Boxes, do without any heſitation fetch them thence upon occaſion, extending hands to the right Box. The hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Simonides</hi> of <hi>Chios</hi> is very pertinent to this purpoſe, who being at Supper among many other Gueſts, at a wealthy mans houſe named <hi>Scope,</hi> was acquainted two young men attended at the door to ſpeak with him; <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi> ariſing from the Table went to them; whiles he was at the door, the Gueſts were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſlain by a ſudden fall of the chamber, whereby their bodies were ſo bruiſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced that they could not be diſtinguiſhed one from another when their friends came to bury them; but <hi>Simonides</hi> bearing well in mind in what place each of them was ſeated, point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the bodies of them all, and was hereby firſt admoniſhed, that <hi>Places</hi> and order might be very advantagious to quicken <hi>Memory.</hi> He alſo left to poſterity ſome Precepts of the <hi>Art of Memory,</hi> which are all ſince drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the deep gulph of <hi>Antiquity.</hi> Another ſingular example correſpondent in ſome ſort to this, is the Election of <hi>Darius</hi> to the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41178:5"/>Monarchy; <hi>Cambyſes</hi> being dead (as ſaith <hi>Herodotus</hi>) it was concluded among the ſeven <hi>Perſian</hi> Princes, next morning to take horſe together, and to ride forth of the City, unanimouſly agreeing the chief ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, without any further conteſt, ſhould reſide in him whoſe Horſe firſt neighed. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> one of the ſeven, through the craft of his Groom <hi>Oebares,</hi> obteined the Supremacy. <hi>Oebares</hi> was a ſubtil wilie fellow, to whom <hi>Darius</hi> diſcovered the whole buſineſs, and warned him to uſe all diligence to prevent his Competitors: <hi>Oebares</hi> deſired him to take no care, for he would effectuate his ſo much deſired deſign: Before night <hi>Oebares</hi> led forth a Mare, chiefly affected by <hi>Darius</hi> his Horſe, and tied her in the high-way, through which the Princes were to ride next morning; afterward he brought forth <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his Horſe, and leaving him at liberty, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him to cover the mare. At Sun-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſeven Princes of <hi>Perſia</hi> mounted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and rode forth of the City; when they came to the place where <hi>Oebares</hi> had tied the Mare the night before; immediately <hi>Darius</hi> his horſe began to neigh, and preſently the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes, as hearing ſome divine Oracle, alighted, and ſaluted him King. This exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if I am not deceived, doth ſufficiently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
<pb facs="tcp:41178:5"/>the utility of <hi>Places</hi> to rouſe up <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> ſeeing even bruit beaſts remember things placed by the place.</p>
            <p>Further, that <hi>Memory</hi> is quickned by <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's</hi> is thus manifeſt: No man is ignorant, that <hi>Memory</hi> is ſtronger converſant about ſenſible things then about inſenſible; and of ſenſible things, thoſe which are viſible make deepeſt impreſſion; therefore things heard are more firmly retained in <hi>Memory,</hi> then thoſe which are barely conceived in mind, &amp; things ſeen better then thoſe which are heard, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Poet:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Segnius irritant animos dimiſſa per aures,</l>
               <l>Quam quae ſunt oculis ſubjecta fidelibus,</l>
               <l>Et quae ipſe ſibi tradit ſpectator.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Things heard in mind no ſuch impreſſion make,</l>
               <l>As thoſe whereof our faithful eyes partake,</l>
               <l>And whereof we our ſelves ſpectators are.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>For this cauſe <hi>Phyſicians</hi> perſwade Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Phyſick, not only to read over the works of <hi>Hippocrtes, Galen</hi> and other moſt skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Phyſicians, Philoſophers, Anatomiſts Herbariſts,</hi> &amp; to frequent publick <hi>Lectures,</hi> but alſo to be preſent at <hi>Diſſections,</hi> and to gather Herbs with their own hands, that they may never after forget, what their eyes have
<pb facs="tcp:41178:6"/>once ſeen. I perſwade the ſame thing in this Book; form a lively <hi>Idea</hi> of that thing which you deſire to remember with an imagination ſo ſtrong, as if you did ſee it indeed: For even as an ember almoſt dead, is reſuſcitated by application of a Match, and breaketh forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a flame; So a <hi>Notion</hi> languiſhing of it ſelf, by mental conſpection of its <hi>Idea,</hi> is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vified, and reaſſumeth ſtrength. Seeing all underſtanding is deduced from external ſence, it doth conſequently follow, that intelligible things reduced to ſenſible, will ſooner inform the underſtanding. Hence the Holy Ghoſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting himſelf to humane capacity, doth oftentimes in Scripture attribute cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal members and external ſences to God himſelfe, and to inviſible Spirits; Becauſe we do better underſtand the nature of ſuch things veiled in that manner with ſenſible things. I omit the <hi>Imaginative</hi> faculty is ſo called of framing <hi>Idea's</hi> or Images in the Brain; As alſo that <hi>Intellect</hi> is ſaid to be derived <hi>ab interna lectione Idearum,</hi> from internal election of Idea's retained in Memory. <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſo far as it is ſtrictly taken for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon receptacle of <hi>Memorandums,</hi> is meerly paſſive, and doth retain and conſerve imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Notions, tranſmitted thereunto by the underſtanding, in the ſame manner as Paper
<pb facs="tcp:41178:6"/>preſerveth words written therein. As it is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Scribe, not of Paper, to write, and read things written; ſo to diſpoſe Idea's in Memory, and aptlp to uſe them, is the work of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not of Memory. Why are there any memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable monuments extant, as it were truly viſible Idea's, by which the memory of things paſt are committed to poſterity? Thus the Funeral Pile of <hi>Semiramis,</hi> and the Columns of <hi>Hercules</hi> have preſerved the memory of them both in ſucceeding ages. Thus in ſacred ſtory we read that twelve Stones were reared in the River <hi>Jordan</hi> for a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing monument of the Iſraelites paſſage, <hi>Joſh. 4.9.</hi> Alſo that a great ſtone was placed under an Oak, in memory of the peoples Covenant with God, <hi>Joſh. 24.27.</hi> Why elſe were Sacraments or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by God, but as viſible Idea's of inviſible things, whereby he admoniſheth us, too forgetful of his beneſits? Laſtly it is a common thing, even amongſt illiterate and ignorant men, to remember things by Idea's. One being to keep in mind the name of a certain man called, <hi>Fiſher,</hi> to imprint this name deeper in memory, thinketh of a Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man placing his Nets. Another having ſome bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs committed to his care, which he feareth to forget, bindeth a Ribbon or Thred about his little finger, by ſight of which viſible Idea he is admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of his charge. Whence it is apparent, that the excogitation of Idea's to fix things in memory, is
<pb facs="tcp:41178:7"/>in ſome ſort natural, ſeing Nature it ſelf hath taught men, deſtitute of Learning, to uſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now there onely remaineth Anſwers to Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by which the Adverſaries of this Art in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to obumbrate the luſtre, and diminiſh the credit thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt they object, that the faculty of Natural <hi>Memory</hi> and Ingenuity, by uſe of this Art, is unmeaſurably impaired; for ſuch Authors as have treated of this Art, do uſually preſcribe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of a multitude of <hi>Places,</hi> wherein occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Idea's</hi> of <hi>Memorandums</hi> may be diſtributed to remain alwaies, with a weekly, or at leaſt month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peruſal, or over-looking of them all, leaſt at any time they ſhould be forgotten, which is certainly a tranſcendent labour, and muſt needs dull the edge of humane underſtanding. To which I anſwer, I am of the ſame opinion; to wit, that if any man indeavour to retain all things he deſireth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member by <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Idea's,</hi> to be reviewed once a month, he undertaketh a work that would weary the dulleſt witted men, much more ingenious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who loath nothing more then frequent medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of things formerly learned; It is alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, becauſe writing of things worthy, memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in books, is much eaſier, more certain and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier for uſe. The way of <hi>Memory</hi> I preſcribe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> onely to preſerve things lately heard, read, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented,
<pb facs="tcp:41178:7"/>until they may be tranſcribed, that the mind ſinking under this burthen, may be relieved as ſpeedily as may be. Moreaver it is certain, that the virtue of natural Memory is very much corroborated by this way of Remembring propoſed in this book: For the mind being daily accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to <hi>Revocation</hi> of ſentences ſlipped out of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and that of thy a word or two, is more enabled in diſcharge of its office, then is credible to one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>experienced, whereby alſo wit is more and more exacuated. Neither have I uſed any principles in this Art prejudicial to the faculty of Memory; but do rather admoniſh you not to uſe them, leaſt they procure great damage to your natural Memory.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they ſay it is a great trouble, in the Ropoſition of one Idea, to enter upon two or three conſiderations. I anſwer, that they which ſpeak Latine, obſerve a manifold conſtruction of words, yet do readily pronounce each word in its caſe, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, number, perſon, and tenſe, without ſtudy; nor is the Memory thereby any way confounded, becauſe they are frequently converſant in practice of Grammar rules; In like manner, when all the rules of the Art of Memory are exactly known, it will not be difficult to attire all Idea's with their proper circumſtances.</p>
            <p>If any man blame or accuſe me as diſſenting from <hi>Logicians,</hi> who affirm that any thing may
<pb facs="tcp:41178:8"/>be kept in memory by help of Logical method, he is much miſtaken; for it is evident they ſpeak onely of long ſpeeches; But no ſober man did ever aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that method was ſufficient to remember com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon buſineſſes, words, phraſes, numbers, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſentences, all which things are faithfully kept in memory by Idea's aptly diſpoſed. The dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of method reſerved (which I acknowledged to be very great) it cannot be denied, but the very method of a long Oration partly forgotten, may be recalled to mind, by the order of diſpoſed I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, it is a fantaſtical buſineſs to be imploied in excogitating and compoſing toyes, and therefore this is not worthy to be called an Art, which is occupied in ſuch trifles. How, I pray, is the Art of Memory wholly fantaſtical, when it is onely buſied in framing phancies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by phantaſie is aided to ſerve the memory more faithfully? That this is an Art, I prove thus; <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Memory</hi> are diſtinct faculties of the mind, though not divided aſunder; Therefore if there be any Art to inform <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as ſuch is <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick,</hi> why not alſo an Art to inform <hi>Memory</hi> as this is?</p>
            <p>Laſtly if any man ask, what cauſe moved me to divulge this Art, my anſwer is, that having di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently read over all the books, I could procure of this Art, and beſtowed much labour, with great
<pb facs="tcp:41178:8"/>loſs of time, beſides great defatigation of mind, in practiſing other mens precepts, when I perceived ſome things impious, obſcure, and ſuperfluous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this Art; alſo many things very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary quite omitted, with ſo much confuſion and diſorder, that ſcarcely any certainty could be found wherein to inſiſt, I did heartily deſire to raiſe this excellent Art out of the thick fogge wherein it was inveloped, and eliminate all its ſuperfluities wherewith it was defiled. Accordingly I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took it at leiſure hours, and by diſmiſſing ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundancies, and ſupplying defects, have reduced it into a new and (if I be not deceived) much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter form, which experience having proved very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to my ſelf, I conceived might alſo profit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and therefore have boldly publiſhed the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the things I had to ſay in approbation of artificial memory, whence I think doth ſufficiently appear, that the principles hereof are derived from the moſt internal Fountains of Art and Nature. Such as have good natural memories, may well want the uſe of this Art, like as healthy people need no phyſick; but it will be of ſingular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to ſuch as have dull, remiſs momories, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if they be quickned and ſharpned by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent practice of this Art from theit younger years. No man is indued with ſo happy a Memory, but he may improve it by this Art; for as all liberal ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb facs="tcp:41178:9"/>help nature to perfection, by demonſtrating ſome more accompliſhed method then Nature it ſelf hath taught, ſo alſo this; Men compoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments naturally, but learn to argue better by <hi>Logick;</hi> ſo though Nature teach us to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, yet we learn to commit things to Memory more ſurely, by benefit of this Art. How mean ſoever theſe things are, expoſed in the enſuing Books, they have been divulged with a deſire of your Utility; It is your part therefore, to take my indeavours and labours in good part, as I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it mine, to give glory to God in all things, and to look upon him as the Author of all good Arts, and the Fountain of Wiſdome:</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell:</salute>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41178:9"/>
            <head>The Art of Memory. The firſt Book.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of remembring common affairs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MNemonica,</hi> or artificial Memorie, ſo far as it falleth under our preſent conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is two-fold: in <hi>Writing,</hi> or without <hi>Writing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Written</hi> way of <hi>Remembring,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth on naked hand-writing, which is more certain and facil then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and therefore alwaies to be uſed when oportunity doth permit. In treating hereof, it were ſuperfluous to ſpeak of writing notes ſuperfluous to ſpeak of writing notes in Table-books, or to purſue every trivial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but onely deliver ſuch things as ſeem more uſefull: Firſt I will handle <hi>Notation</hi> of common buſineſs, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch things as pertain to learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41178:10"/>
               <p> Concerning the former of theſe two I will onely adde one precept, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch as are in frequent uſe, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide an Almanack with blank pages, in which every evening, againſt the proper day of the moneth, ſet down your chiefeſt buſineſs of that day, and alſo the names of ſuch perſons as you have converſed with about any ſerious affair, either at home or abroad. Though the utility hereof be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conſpicuous, yet many times afterward, it is of great conſequence to reſolve difficulties of very great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. Suppoſe that after ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of time, three months, a year or more, queſtion ariſe about the very day whereon ſuch or ſuch a thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, an exact knowledg whereof will be very profitable; the certain day you have forgotten, but well remember it was on the ſame day your ſheep were ſhorn, or the day after ſuch friends di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with you; this being conſidered, your Almanack will exhibit the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular day. Moreover by the mens names with whom you ſpake that day, haply you may learn many things moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be known in the preſent cauſe.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41178:10"/>
               <p> This briefly ſhal ſuffice concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring ordinary buſineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of remembring Words.</head>
               <p>THere are four kinds of <hi>Memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dums</hi> belonging to Diſcipline, or Learning: Words, Phraſes, Sentences, and Set-Speeches.</p>
               <p>A Word may be remembred by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation</hi> or <hi>Connexion. Derivation</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or Improper; <hi>Proper Derivation</hi> is an apt interpretation of Words; as <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex</hi> an <hi>Harlot,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a word compounded of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the diviſion of man and wife; or if you pleaſe of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an Harlot is a Divided Wife. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>bleſſed,</hi> as it were of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal: Filii</hi> and <hi>filiae,</hi> Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from the love they procure between Parents<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>vir</hi> a Man, <hi>à viribus; Mulier</hi> a Woman, <hi>quaſi mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior,</hi> from the Sexes tenderneſs; <hi>Puer</hi> a Boy, <hi>à puritate corporis; Panis</hi> Bread, of <hi>Pan,</hi> who (as <hi>Olaus Magnus</hi> ſaith) firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41178:11"/>the Bakers Art; <hi>Popa</hi> a Glutton or Victualler, from <hi>Popina</hi> a Cooks-ſhop; <hi>Lucus</hi> a Grove, <hi>à lucendo,</hi> for it proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifieth a place planted with trees, enlightned with Torches, and hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſome Idol: <hi>Babble</hi> of <hi>Babel;</hi> a <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier</hi> of <hi>Soldurius,</hi> who ſerved under <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Ceſ. Com.</hi> or if you had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>quaſi ſole duratus; Church,</hi> antient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Kirk,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſup.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Lord's-houſe; <hi>Neighbour,</hi> as it were <hi>nigh</hi> thy <hi>bower,</hi> a word formerly uſed for a dwelling houſe; <hi>Goſpel,</hi> of <hi>good ſpel,</hi> antiently uſed for <hi>ſpeech</hi> or <hi>tidings; Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge,</hi> of <hi>parting</hi> a <hi>ridge,</hi> for they are u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually found in ridges of Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Improper Derivation,</hi> is a ſtrained in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of a word; as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe after ſacrifice they feaſted their pallates; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſmoke,</hi> as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſteam of ſomething burning; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Lachrimae à lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando,</hi> ſo <hi>Tears</hi> in Engliſh, of <hi>tearing</hi> the <hi>heart: Monumentum quaſi monens mentem; Domus</hi> ex <hi>do</hi> &amp; <hi>mus; Cottage</hi> as it were a <hi>coat</hi> for <hi>age: Beer</hi> as it were <hi>Bee-here; Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſip</hi> of <hi>go-ſip; Simony</hi> as it were <hi>See-mony;</hi> and Derivation howſoever abſurd or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41178:11"/>wreſted, printeth words in Memory; yea the further it is fetched, the deeper impreſſion it maketh.</p>
               <p>A Word is retained by <hi>Connexion,</hi> when it is aptly compoſed in a ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other words: <hi>Homer</hi> ſaid well, <hi>Words have wings,</hi> both becauſe being ſpoken, they cannot be recalled; and that if they be neglected in the ſcope of ſentences, they are forgotten: for example, let theſe words <hi>Oeſtrum</hi> a Gad-bee, and <hi>Cynomya</hi> an Horſe-flie, be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to be remembred, they may be comprehended in a ſentence thus; <hi>Viminia tibi lotione macerantur, quae cynomya adeoque etiam oeſtro vehement ius pungent;</hi> Rods ſteeped in piſs, ſting worſe then a Horſe-flye or Gad-bee: So theſe words, <hi>Vitricus</hi> a Father-in-law, <hi>Acupedius</hi> a Footman, <hi>illunis</hi> moonleſs, are thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in a ſentence; <hi>Illunis licet, ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris tamen nox erat, quâ Acupedius ad Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trici aedes deflecteret;</hi> It was a light night, though the moondid not ſhine, in which the Footman called at my Father in law his houſe. Again, ſuppoſe theſe words to be kept in mind; <hi>Alyptes</hi> a Surgeon, <hi>ſuccenturiatus</hi> ſubſtituted, <hi>tympanotriba</hi> a Drummer, <hi>ſtrigoſus</hi> bare bone: they may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41178:12"/>be thus framed into a Sentence; <hi>Aly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptes ſtrigoſus in locum tympanotribae caeſi ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centuriatus eſt;</hi> A bare-boned Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon was ſubſtituted in place of the ſlain Drummer. This is a profitable kind of exerciſe for unknown, out-worn, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign or ſeldom uſed words, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur ſometimes in reading, and are to be obſerved, that they may be better known. Learners, who ſtudy the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive words of any Language; as <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Greek,</hi> or <hi>Hebrew,</hi> may reap no ſmal benefit by <hi>Derivation</hi> and <hi>Connexion</hi> of words, if they imitate the following method Having provided a Paper-book to contain the Primitive words, divide every page into three Columns, of which let the third be broadeſt: In the firſt columne write down the Primitive words, in the ſecond their ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in the third their Etymologies, or Derivations. But if you meet with any word that doth not preſently admit Derivation either Proper, or Improper, leave the ſpace in the third columne void, and paſs on to the next word, that you may not loſe time by a perplexed indagation of the Etymology: Then col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect all the words you find in the page,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41178:12"/>which decline Derivation, into one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, ſo by Connexion you may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print thoſe words in Memory, which you cannot by Derivation. Every ſuch ſentence muſt be written at the bottom of the page; I will give you an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the firſt twelve primitive words of the Greek tongue, as they are exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in the Catalogue of <hi>John Surcinus,</hi> in this order.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>to exhale,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>from the feigned ſound wee make in breathing. <hi>Scap.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>to hurt,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>of <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, the firſt <hi>Paſſive Ao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,</hi> of the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>to hurt,</hi> according to the <hi>Ionick</hi> dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>kind,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>of <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> the privative particle, and <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>envious.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>to meet,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>of <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, ſignifying the ſame.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>a Maidſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, delicate.</cell>
                        <cell>Theſe words have a manifeſt Relation one to the other.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Theſe words have a manifeſt Relation one to the other.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>fooliſh.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>a heap.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41178:13"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>good:</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>As it were <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>Divine;</hi> or of <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>to be admired;</hi> hence cometh our <hi>Engliſh</hi> word <hi>Agaſt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Overmuch:</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Hence cometh our <hi>Engliſh</hi> word, <hi>Again,</hi> and <hi>Again.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>to love.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Poſts:</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>From <hi>Angeri,</hi> to afflict, for ſo they do their Horſes with their Spurs; and hence may come our Engliſh word <hi>Angry.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; What ſhould a fool do with heaps of goods?</p>
               <p>Here you may ſee two words admitting no derivation, comprehended in one Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; but the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to love,</hi> is ſo frequent, it needeth no connexion. The manner of exerciſe to learn theſe, is thus: Firſt, lay a flat Ruler, or your finger, over the middle Column, in ſuch ſort, that the words of the firſt and third Column (which contain the primitives &amp; their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivations) may appear on both ſides; by mutual compariſon of which, you muſt try to inveſtigate the ſignifications latent under the Ruler: Afterward conceal the firſt Column in like manner, that by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41178:13"/>comparing the ſignifications and deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions lying in ſight, you may ſtudy the primitive words latent under the Ruler or your finger. If you diſpatch but one page a day after this order, (which is ſcarcely an hours work in few dayes you may fix all the primitive words of the whole tongue in your mind without any labor, nay rather with delight. If you can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſome companions in ſcrutinie, of the derivations, equally lovers of the ſame ſtudy, your labour will be rendered much more delectable and facile.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of remembring Phraſes.</head>
               <p>A Phraſe may be committed to memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by accommodating it to ſome fit ſubject; as if this phraſe were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, <hi>Very much eſtranged from filthy affections;</hi> I apply it to a Chriſtian Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, as to a meet ſubject in this manner, <hi>A Chriſtian Souldier ought to be very much eſtranged from all filthy and ſordid affections of mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41178:14"/>
               <p> Or this example, To forgoe manhood through effeminate delicacy, may be fitly accommodated to <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria;</hi> thus <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> by effeminate delicacy and luxury, loſt all manhood, and led a Womaniſh life.</p>
               <p>Again, this example, A man furniſhed with abundant ſtore of Learning, may be thus applyed; <hi>Uſher</hi> the renowned Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> was furniſhed with abundant ſtore of good Literature, and manifold Learning; ſo that he did juſtly bear the prize from moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>relates of the World.</p>
               <p>This manner of applying Phraſes, is principally neceſſary in learning the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of any Tongue, and is very well worthy to be more frequently uſed in publike Schools: I confeſs Maſters do u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually command their Schollars to collect phraſes and elegant ſentences out of their Lectures, and to write their gleanings in Books, not in looſe Papers, which is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what; but if they did, alſo urge them to refer every phraſe by them collected, to ſome friend or acquaintance, they would by this means reap a far greater Harveſt of Learning: For phraſes thus accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated, ſink deeper, and continue lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in memory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41178:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of remembring Sentences.</head>
               <p>SEntences worthy of Memory, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther frequently or ſeldom uſed: Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of common uſe (I mean ſuch as we deſire to preſerve not onely in paper, but in our hearts, becauſe of their ſingular Elegancy, ſerious Gravity, conciſe brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or witty ingenuity) are to be ſtored in a Manual every kind in a peculiar place: Epigrams by themſelves, Anagrams by themſelves, ſo Proverbs, Epitaphs, Jeſts, Riddles, Obſervations, &amp;c. by themſelves: This <hi>Enchiridion</hi> wherein you write ſuch remarkable ſentences, ought always to be carryed about you, (and may therefore be called, <hi>Vade mecum</hi>) that you may peruſe the ſame at leiſure-hours when you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, not having other employment; by which means, Time, moſt precious of all things, will not be unprofitably ſpent: And hereby you will keep in mind things worthy remembrance, better, ſafer, ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, more certainly, profitably, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully, then by that monſtrous repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41178:15"/>preſcribed by ſome Authors in this Art of Memory, which nevertheleſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be effected without long ſtudy, very great defatigation of the underſtanding &amp; pernicious damage of the memorative fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; beſides, a perpetual Oblivion of ſome <hi>Idea's,</hi> occaſioned by ſo long ſpace of time interpoſed.</p>
               <p>A ſentence ſeldom uſed, is either an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of ſome Claſſick Author, or a common Obſervation; by Claſſick Books or Authors, I mean thoſe which are accounted Authentick by common conſent of profeſſors in every Science; ſuch are the Scriptures among Divines, Decrees and Statutes among Lawyers, the works of <hi>Hypocrates, Galen,</hi> or <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> among Phyſicians: <hi>Euclids</hi> Elements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Mathematicians, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If you meet with any memorable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of a Claſſick Book, note it down in ſhort hand in the Margent, near the Text to which it properly relateth; or if you had rather, cauſe clean paper to be bound between every leaf, to receive ſuch Comments: Or, (which is better) have plenty of white Paper bound at the end of the Book, in which write your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and relate them to the text
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41178:15"/>by like numbers or letters prefixed before the Notes and Text.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V:</hi> Of remembring long Speeches.</head>
               <p>NOw laſtly, I will treat of <hi>Speeches;</hi> A ſpeech, according to my acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is any large Treatiſe compoſed of many ſentences of one kind; ſuch are <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Orations, Declarations, Heads,</hi> or <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> of Books; or finally, any long Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, or memorable Speeches, are either ſuch as are framed by our ſelves, or by others: Again, Speeches of other men are either extant in Books, or are deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by word of mouth.</p>
               <p>If the Speeches to be remembred, are already extant in print, it is ſufficient to ſet down their Titles in your Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place-Book, under their proper Heads, to advertiſe you in what Chapter or part of a Book, this, or that Argument is more largely handled: As for example, In the firſt Book of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Inſtitutions, and thirteenth Chapter, the three perſons of the Godhead in one Eſſence, is proved by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41178:16"/>divers reaſons; to tranſcribe which Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, though in Epitome, would be very laborious: Therefore it is better under the title of Trinity, among other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon obſervations pertaining to the ſame purpoſe, to write down theſe words, <hi>That three Perſons are contained in one onely Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God,</hi> Cal. Inſtitut. Lib. 1. Cap. 13. By which Citation you are directed to that place of <hi>Calvin</hi> whenſoever you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>If the Speech you deſire to preſerve be verbally pronounced, you muſt take it in ſhort-hand, if you have skill; otherwiſe in long hand, with as much celerity as you can: If you be at any time left behind through nimble volubility of the Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers tongue, it will be ſufficient to write onely the eſſential words of every Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence (as for the moſt part are Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Verbs) leaving vacant ſpaces, in which either words of leſs weight may be interpoſed, which muſt be ſupplyed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Speech is ended.</p>
               <p>Four things muſt be obſerved, that ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches contrived by our ſelves, may be deeply faſtened in memory; <hi>Method, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Marginal Notation,</hi> and <hi>Meditation;</hi> the <hi>Method</hi> ought to be ſo diſpoſed, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41178:16"/>part of an entire Speech, and every ſentence of thoſe parts, precede accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their dignity in nature; that is, that every thing be ſo placed, that it may give light to underſtand what followeth: Such a method is very effectual to eaſe the memory both of Speaker and Hearer; for in a ſpeech methodically digeſted, each ſentence attracteth the next, like as one link draweth another in a Golden Chain, therefore <hi>Method</hi> is called the <hi>Chain of Memory:</hi> For this cauſe let every former ſentence ſo depend on the latter, that it may ſeem neceſſarily related thereunto.</p>
               <p>In writing a Speech, let your firſt care be, that your Lines extend not too far, but that ſpace enough be left in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: In the next place, that your whole ſpeech be diſtinguiſhed into heads; for a diſtinct mind apprehendeth better then one confuſed. After you have compiled a Speech you are ſhortly to deliver, do not tranſcribe it, though it be both blotted and interlined, leſt you loſe as much time in new Writing, as would ſuffice to learn it: Beſides the blots and interlining do more firmly faſten in mind the ſentences ſo blotted and interlined, then if they were otherwiſe. This is alſo to be noted,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41178:17"/>that although it be neceſſary to write o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the intire Speech, or at leaſt, brief notes thereof, before it be publikely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; yet ought that <hi>Tranſcription</hi> by no means to be ſeen publikely, unleſs <hi>Memory</hi> languiſh, and be weak: For the mind doth better recollect it ſelf in the abſence of Notes, and by united force is better prepared to ſpeak.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marginal Notation</hi> is when one or two chief words of every ſentence is placed in the Margent, which ſo ſoon as ſeen, (which is with the leaſt caſt of an eye) revoketh the whole ſentence to mind: As if this enſuing ſmall Treatiſe of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> were to be learned by heart; I diſtinguiſh the ſentences thereof by words placed in the Margent, by which means they are ſpeedily remembred.</p>
               <p>That there ſhall be a Reſurrection of the dead at the laſt day, is confirmed by theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Becauſe it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.</note>Firſt, that which is imperfect, is unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of perfect felicity in its kind; but the ſoul ſeparate from the body is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and therefore not capable of perfect felicity. Thence followeth a neceſſity of the Bodies Reſurrection, that by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction thereof with the Soul, the Elect
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41178:17"/>may enjoy perfect felicity: <hi>How are they happy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) <hi>if they ſhall periſh in part?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Seals of Salvation.</note>Secondly, If the Body by Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ought to be as well partaker of the ſeals of ſalvation, as the Soul; then it ſhall as well participate of Eternal Salvation; but the Body, according to Chriſts inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, ought to partake of the ſeals of ſalvation: For the Body is waſhed with water of Baptiſm, and nouriſhed by Bread and Wine in the Lords Supper: <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">As Seeds.</note>Thirdly, Like as Seeds caſt into the Earth dye, and revive again; ſo humane bodies buried in the ground, diſſolved and corrupted, ſhall riſe again at the laſt day, by the quickening virtue of Chriſt: <hi>Paul</hi> brandeth him with folly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.35. who cannot conclude the reſurrection of the dead out of the vivification of Seeds bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the ground;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.35.</note> whence <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> 
                  <hi>He which viviſieth dead and putrified Seeds by which men live in this world, more facilely will raiſe you up to live eternally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things.</note>Fourthly, The Revolution of all things is an argument of the Reſurrection; as Day followeth night, Waking Sleep, Reſt Labor, and Winter Summer; ſo Life fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41178:18"/>
                  <hi>death,</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection Sepulture.</hi> That which <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaketh in his Book <hi>Of the Reſurrection of the fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> is pertinent hereto; <hi>Day</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dyeth into night, yet is enlivened again with glorie all over the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, It is evidently proved by the <hi>Reſurrection of Chriſt;</hi> ſeeing Chriſt, which is our head, is already riſen, it is a teſtimony that we alſo, who are his members, ſhall live after death. Where the head is, thither will the members be gathered;<note place="margin">Chriſt our head. 1 Cor. 15.20.</note> in this reſpect Chriſt is termed <hi>the firſt fruits of the dead,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note>Sixthly, The particular <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of ſome, to a temporal life in this world, was a ſign of the general <hi>Reſurrection</hi> to eternal life to be at the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Theſe were raiſed again after death.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The ſon of the widow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 18.22.</item>
                  <item>2. The ſon of the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.33.</item>
                  <item>3. A certain man by the touch of <hi>Elias</hi> bones, 2 <hi>King</hi> 13.21.</item>
                  <item>4. The ſon of the widow of <hi>Naim, Luke</hi> 7.15.</item>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41178:18"/>
                  <item>5. The daughter of <hi>Jairus, Luke</hi> 8.48.</item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Lazarus, John</hi> 11 43.</item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Tabitha, Acts</hi> 9.40.</item>
                  <item>8. <hi>Eutichus, Acts</hi> 20.10.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who though.</note>All which, though they dyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, after their <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> yet may we not think thoſe Saints dyed any more, of whom mention is made, <hi>Matt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Saints cut of their Tombs.</note> 27.52. who roſe out of their Tombs after <hi>Chriſts Reſurrection,</hi> that they might paſſe to eternall life with him, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of whoſe <hi>Reſurrection</hi> they were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>Finally, there are almoſt innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble places of Scripture,<note place="margin">Places of Scripture,</note> which may be produced to evince to the certainty of this Article, of which I will onely cite a few at preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job</hi> 19.25, 26, 27. <hi>For I am ſure that my Redeemer liveth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 19.25.</note> 
                  <hi>and he ſhall ſtand the laſt on the earth; and though worms deſtroy this body, yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh, whom I my ſelf ſhall ſee, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and none other for me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſaiah, 26.19. <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.19</note> 
                  <hi>even with my body ſhall they riſe: awake and ſing, ye that dwell in duſt, for thy dew is as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41178:19"/>the dew of herbs, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ezek.<note place="margin">Ezek. 37.5.</note> 37.5, 6. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God unto theſe bones, behold, I will cauſe breath to enter into you, and ye ſhall live. And I will lay ſinews upon you, and make fleſh grow upon you, and cover you with skin, and put breath in you, that ye may live, and ye ſhall know that I am the Lord.</hi> Theſe quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were indeed ſpoken to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Exekiel,</hi> of the <hi>Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the people out of Captivity, nevertheleſſe thereby the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is evidently confirmed;<note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that muſt be neceſſarily firſt, which illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth another; a <hi>Similitude, Compariſon, Metaphor,</hi> or <hi>Allegory,</hi> cannot be dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of nothing.</p>
               <p>Dan. 12.2. <hi>And many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 12.2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall awake, ſome to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual contempt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>John 5 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">John. 5.28</note> 
                  <hi>For the hour ſhall come in the which all that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice, and they ſhall come forth that have done good, unto the reſurrection of life, but they that have done evil, unto the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of condemnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41178:19"/>
               <p> 1 Cor. 15. <hi>Paul</hi> in that whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> treateth of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the body, and eſtabliſheth the ſame by many reaſons, which I will not preſſe further, but onely reply to a common argument of Atheiſts, wherewith they do ſtubbornly ſeal up their hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this truth.</p>
               <p>They Object,<note place="margin">Object. Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</note> that oft times the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of many are buried in one and the ſame monument, whoſe carcaſſes muſt inevitably be commixed by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; that the bodies of ſome are burned to aſhes, that others are drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſea, and devoured of fiſhes, thoſe fiſhes perchance of men, and thoſe men of beaſts and ravens; laſtly, that there are men in ſome Regions who eat humane fleſh, by which means the ſubſtance of one muſt be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily converted into the ſubſtance of the other; How then ſay they, is it poſſible, that every mans proper body ſhould be reſtored in fire?</p>
               <p>I anſwer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Above our capacity.</note> that the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is a work above mans capacity, whereof we are no more able to aſſign a certain rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than of the worlds creation; wherefore though the above recited
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41178:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41178:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41178:21"/>things ſeem impoſſible to us to be done, yet all things are poſſible to God. You may ask, ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> upon the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyps,</hi> how matter when it is diſſolved, may be reſtored?<note place="margin">Tertullian</note> I reply, you who once were not, are made, and ſo when you ceaſe to be, ſhall be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, we ſee that a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Alchymiſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alchymiſt</note> by his <hi>Chymical</hi> art, can ſeperate and extract Gold, Silver, Tinne, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> each ſeverally apart out of the ſame maſſe; cannot God then produce out of the Elements humane bodies, how many alterations ſoever they undergo? ſeeing the bodies of the dead are onely changed, never reduced to nothing.</p>
               <p>God created light out of darkneſſe, ill things out of nothing,<note place="margin">Light out of darknes</note> power out of weakneſſe, grace out of ſinne, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured us a bleſſed life out of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours curſed death. Shall not any thing be poſſible to him? It is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſecret part.</note>I conclude, At the final <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> every perſon ſhall have a ſecret portion of his body, out of which by operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Divine Omnipotencie, it may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41178:21"/>be formed a new intire,<note place="margin">Of the Rib.</note> ſo that a man may be perfect. He which created the woman of the mans rib, and cauſe a grain of <hi>Muſtard-ſeed</hi> to become a ſtately plant, can alſo compoſe an intire body of the leaſt part of one. Like as in the ſeed of plants, there is ſome hidden thing by which they dayly gain vigour and grow;<note place="margin">As in the ſeeds of Plants.</note> ſo there is ſome hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thing in every humane body, out of which the body (diſſolved) will be again new made.<note place="margin">Aquinas.</note> 
                  <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it is the primary being of each per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which being reſtored to every one in the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> will be dilated in an inſtant, as <hi>Adams</hi> rib in the womans creation, and the loaves of <hi>Elizeus</hi> and Chriſt,<note place="margin">Loaves.</note> with which ſo many were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. What nature produceth by long intervals of time, God can effect in an inſtant.</p>
               <p>Thus having diſpatched Marginal notes, I deſcend to <hi>Meditation,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, take theſe following <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 1. After you have copied over your whole Speech or Sermon, aptly divided into heads, and marked the principall words of each ſentence in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41178:22"/>the <hi>Margent,</hi> go diligently to meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, trying whether you can repeat all the Sentences in their order by bare ſight of the Marginall notes. You need not be ſollicitous of every word, ſo that you do accurately remember the ſenſe or ſcope, becauſe the minde eſteemeth it an unworthy thraledom to be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to every conceived word; <hi>Horace</hi> hath moſt truly ſaid,</p>
               <q>Rem bene praeviſam verba haud invita ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentur.</q>
               <q>The ſcope foreſeen, words readily occur.</q>
               <p>But if you ſtick at any place, read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſentence (which the Marginall note doth not ſuggeſt) with no leſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and attention of minde, than if you had never ſeen the ſame. I dare promiſe ſuch manner of proceeding in Meditation will produce more happy ſucceſs, then Opinion can readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: If you do not benefit your ſelf by <hi>Marginal notes</hi> either in Learning a Speech or Sermon, you will make ſlow progreſs, and be ſenſible of very great
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41178:22"/>trouble in Meditation; whereas by their help, you may fix ſentences in Memory with great celerity (not to ſay, with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) as you may make an experiment, if you pleaſe, in the foregoing Tractate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 2. The manner of <hi>Meditating,</hi> is to learn by parts; That is, Firſt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the firſt Section to <hi>Memory,</hi> then the Second, afterward the Third, and ſo forth; the reſt in their order: When you have diſpatched all the heads ſeverally, apply your ſelf to repeat the whole, obſerving <hi>Quintilians</hi> method, to learn with <hi>low voice</hi> and <hi>ſoft murmure,</hi> whereby <hi>Memory</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitted with the double motion of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and hearing. This counſel ſeems e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially appropriated to ſuch whoſe minds are ſlippery, and ſubject to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſtarting preſently aſide, if they be not thus reſtrained; on the contrary, fixed ſtable minds will experience ſilent <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> the more ſpeedy and efficacious way to imprint <hi>Notions</hi> in <hi>Memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 3. Furthermore ſeeing a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and earneſt application of mind is required in <hi>Meditation,</hi> whereby the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are much exhauſted, you muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to avoid longer ſtudy then agreeth with your health, leaſt your ſpirits fail
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41178:23"/>through too great intention of mind: And beware you do not loſe a moment of that little time you aſſign unto Meditation; when you muſt meditate, let it not be with wearineſs, but do that willingly, which you muſt do neceſſarily.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 4. The firſt and laſt hours of the day are moſt apt for Meditation; that is, immediately before and atfer ſleep: Let your firſt Eſſay in Learning your task be at Evening, about an hour after Supper, reading over twice or thrice what you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to commit to Memory againſt the next day, your ſtudy being finiſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take your ſelf to your reſt, that your mind (no other ways diverted) may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon your Evening <hi>Meditation.</hi> In the morning ſo ſoon as you have ſhook off drowzineſs, and prepared your ſelf, repeat thoſe things diligently you medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated the night before. It is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſtudy <hi>before ſleep, unleſs in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you ruminate after ſleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 5. All that ſpeak publickly, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Diſpenſers</hi> of the Word, ought to make it their great care, not to utter things diſorderly, but throughly digeſted by Meditation; leſt they be be like ſuch Cooks as buy good meat in the Shambles,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41178:23"/>but marr it in the Dreſſing, ſending it raw, or half-boiled to the Table. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, if any man appear publickly, either in Pulpit, or otherwiſe, before he is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided what to ſay, he becometh timorous, and the vital ſpirits (the eies of reaſon) have recourſe tot he heart through fear, whereby he is rendred much more unapt to ſpeak then before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 6. Laſtly, which is peculiar in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering Sermons, let Speakers apply more general Doctrines to themſelves jointly with the reſt, in <hi>Confeſſion, Petition, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation, imprecation, interceſſion, thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving</hi> or <hi>praiſing God,</hi> as occaſion is given by the Doctrines themſelvs; ſo they ſhall not onely remember all things bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but alſo edifie their own conſciences; Nay further, frequent uſe of this ioint-application, proveth finally a <hi>Manudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to ſpeak with ſenſe of Divine grace and evidence of Spirit, which is the moſt excellent ornament of a Preacher.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the Firſt Book.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41178:24"/>
            <head>The Art of Memory. The Second Book.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of remembring without writing.</head>
               <p>HAving diſpatched vulgar ways of <hi>Memory,</hi> I deſcend to helps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the ſame purpoſe without <hi>Hand-writing,</hi> which is then moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, when we are deſtitute of the aid of Paper, Ink, or Table-Books, or when by ſome obſtacle we are debarred the free uſe of them. This conſiſteth of two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, <hi>Repoſition</hi> and <hi>Depoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repoſition</hi> is the manner of charging <hi>Memory</hi> with Note-worthy things; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is not to be expected that each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular word of every ſentence be retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; but onely, that the general ſence be faſtened in mind. At all times when a man is about to commit any thing in cuſtody to his <hi>Memory,</hi> firſt let him ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to drown all unneceſſary thoughts in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41178:24"/>oblivion, that he may perfectly intend the things he is to learn; <hi>Oblivion</hi> being ſuch a principle of <hi>Memory,</hi> as <hi>Privati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is of <hi>Generation;</hi> and a ready remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance moſt commonly proceedeth from right underſtanding the thing in hand; therefore a man muſt prepare himſelf diligently, and ſo unite the force of his imagination, that he may as it were engrave and imprint occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things in his Memory. <hi>Lead</hi> doth facily receive impreſſion, becauſe it is tenacious, which <hi>Quick-ſilver</hi> cannot admit, by reaſon of its <hi>Fluxibility:</hi> In like manner fleeting inconſtant minds continually hurried into new &amp; ſtrange cogitations, is far from gathering fruit by any thing heard. The method of a ſpeech is chefly to be obſerved, regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeriouſly what is the general ſubject thereof; Secondly, the greater parts, and with what Logical Arguments each part is handled; the perfect Method of a ſpeech doth much conduce to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the whole; or if the Contexture thereof be inartificial, imperfect, and unſatisfactory, comprehending many things forcibly applied, rejecting things of a like kind, yet a ſtrong Memory will
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41178:25"/>retain the ſame by obſervation of the abſurdities and rude <hi>Artifice</hi> of the whole.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Depoſition</hi> is when we recollect things committed to memory; and having tranſcribed or tranſacted them, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our memories of them, which is alwayes to be practiſed at the firſt opportunity: Things charged in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory by day, are to be depoſited at leaſt before ſleep, if not ſooner; things charged by night, are to be depoſited immediately after ſleep, that the mind be no longer burthened then is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and that things negligently laid up in mind, be not forgotten, <hi>Writing</hi> being the faithfulleſt Guardian of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandums.</hi> If in dis-burthening your Memory, ſomething charged happen to be forgotten, ſhut your eyes, that no no external obiect may divert your mind, and try to recall it by importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſcrutiny; which operation may be called <hi>Revocation,</hi> and is an Art that by help of certain Rules teacheth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtigation of things lapſed out of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>Depoſition,</hi> or diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging things committed to mind, is not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41178:25"/>unlike expunging writing out of Table-Books: If therefore there be any Art of <hi>Oblivion</hi> (as ſome affirm) it may be properly referred hither. So much in general; now to explicate the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſpecies thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of remembring by certain Verſes purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly born in mind.</head>
               <p>THe method of charging Memory without writing, is twofold, <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> and <hi>Ideal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Poetical</hi> way of remembring, is accompliſhed by virtue of Poetry, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Verſes purpoſely afore-compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or <hi>ex tempore.</hi> The manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering by Verſes already compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is when a man doth excogitate or retain remarkable things by repetition of Verſes provided to that purpoſe. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Attorney be to wait upon Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges riding the Circuits from one County to another, it may be worth his labour to repeat theſe verſes at leaving his lodging, leaſt he forget ſome neceſſary
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41178:26"/>thing, which we may imagine formerly framed by him to this end.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Scalpellum, calami, cornugraphium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> libelli,</l>
                  <l>Charta, pugillares, capitalia, cera, ſigillum,</l>
                  <l>Sic crepide, gladius, cultellus, pugio, burſſa,</l>
                  <l>Muccinium, induſium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> monilia, penula, pecten</l>
                  <l>Faſcia cruralis, cruralia, dactylothece.</l>
                  <l>Pen-knife. Quills, Ink-horn, Books, Paper,</l>
                  <l>Table-Books, Caps; Take</l>
                  <l>Wax, Seal and Slippers, Sword, Knife and</l>
                  <l>Dagger, ſafe make</l>
                  <l>Purſe, Handkerchiefs, Shirts, Rings, Coat,</l>
                  <l>and for your own ſake,</l>
                  <l>Comb, Garters, Stockins, Gloves.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Thus a Carpenter oft employed to work abroad, may ingenuouſly make the Tools and Inſtruments belonging to his Art, in Verſe; by repetition of which on occaſion, he may be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed what Tools to take along with him: In like ſort all ordinary buſineſs frequently incumbent upon any man, may be conveniently committed to memory in Verſes, which may adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe him to omit nothing.</p>
               <p>Here I have thought expedient to propoſe certain Verſes lately compoſed by my ſelf, that they may be benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41178:26"/>to others (if they pleaſe) as they have ſometimes been to me, which are theſe.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>An? Quiſ quid? cujus? cui? quo? quibus? auxilijs? cur?</l>
                  <l>Quomodo? circa quid? qualis? quantum? ex, in &amp; a quo?</l>
                  <l>Quamdiu? ubi? quando? quoties? quotu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex? quot &amp; unde?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If? who? what? whoſe? to what? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? why? about what?</l>
                  <l>How? what faſhion? how much? by, of, in, and from what?</l>
                  <l>How long? how often? how manifold? whence came that?</l>
                  <l>Where? when? how many?</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Theſe Verſes (craving the Readers pardon for the ruggedneſs) contain twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two Queſtions of excellent uſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, retain, as alſo to recall to minde things of great concernment and worthy memory in urgent affairs; which being prudently applyed by way of interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do neceſſarily extort the anſwer of all Logical places, which (though I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no man will deny) may be thus illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41178:27"/>
                  <item>1. If there be any ſuch thing?<note place="margin">If?</note> This queſtion is referred to an indefinite argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                  <item>2 Who was Author of the
<list>
                        <item>Motion,<note place="margin">Who?</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>Work,</item>
                        <item>Fact,</item>
                        <item>Saying,</item>
                        <item>Writing,</item>
                        <item>Counſel.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This queſtion reſpecteth the efficient Cauſe. Definition.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>3. What
<list>
                        <item>it is? Effects.</item>
                        <item>doth it contain? Effects.</item>
                        <item>doth depend on it? Effects.</item>
                        <item>is moved? Effects.</item>
                        <item>is done?<note place="margin">What?</note> Effects.</item>
                        <item>is ſpoken? Effects.</item>
                        <item>is written? Effects.</item>
                        <item>is conſulted? Effects.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>4: Whoſe it is?<note place="margin">Whoſe?</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. To what it is compared,<note place="margin">To what?</note> either in
<list>
                        <item>quantity
<list>
                              <item>equal,</item>
                              <item>greater.</item>
                              <item>leſſer.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>quality
<list>
                              <item>like,</item>
                              <item>unlike.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:41178:27"/>
                        <item>6. Whither it tendeth?<note place="margin">Whether?</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. Why the final Cauſe?<note place="margin">Why?</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>8. About what ſubject or object<note place="margin">About What?</note> in
<list>
                              <item>procreating?</item>
                              <item>conſerving?</item>
                              <item>aboliſhing?</item>
                              <item>deſtroying?</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>9. How was it done,
<list>
                              <item>naturally?<note place="margin">How?</note>
                              </item>
                              <item>purpoſely?</item>
                              <item>neceſſarily?</item>
                              <item>accidentally?</item>
                              <item>careleſly?</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>10. VVhat faſhion
<list>
                              <item>form,</item>
                              <item>connexion,<note place="margin">What Faſhion?</note>
                              </item>
                              <item>deſcription?</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>11. How much quantity?</item>
                        <item>12. By what? whether
<list>
                              <item>alone? as principal equal,<note place="margin">How Much? By what?</note> inferior</item>
                              <item>with others? as principal equal, inferior</item>
                              <item>with inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? as principal equal, inferior</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>13. Of what matter?<note place="margin">Of what?</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>14. In what it
<list>
                              <item>is contained?<note place="margin">In what?</note>
                              </item>
                              <item>is exerciſed?</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41178:28"/>
                        <item>15. From what it is is diſtinguiſhed, as
<list>
                              <item>diverſe,</item>
                              <item>unlike,</item>
                              <item>related,</item>
                              <item>contrary,</item>
                              <item>contradictory,</item>
                              <item>privative.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>16. How long?</item>
                        <item>17. How often?</item>
                        <item>18. How manifold? diſtribution
<list>
                              <item>of cauſes,</item>
                              <item>of whole into parts</item>
                              <item>of effects,</item>
                              <item>of genus in ſpecies</item>
                              <item>of ſubjects,</item>
                              <item>of accidents.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>19. Whence
<list>
                              <item>came it?</item>
                              <item>is it derived?</item>
                              <item>is it proved?</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>20. VVhere?</item>
                        <item>21. VVhen?</item>
                        <item>22. How many? induction of
<list>
                              <item>cauſes,</item>
                              <item>parts,</item>
                              <item>effects,</item>
                              <item>ſpecies,</item>
                              <item>ſubjects,</item>
                              <item>accidents.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41178:28"/>
               <p> Hereby it doth accidentally appear, theſe Verſes are both uſeful to recollect things ſlipt out of memory, and alſo to invent new; in handling any ſubject, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things may eſcape our ſcrutiny, which a careful repetition of theſe Verſes, and prudent application, may prompt the mind: As for example, ſuppoſe a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Counſellor were to be conſulted about ſome difficult nice Caſe, in which a man would not willingly omit any material buſineſs, leſt his labor be fruſtrated; let the Interrogations included in theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, be ſeverally applied to the cauſe in controverſie, <hi>viz.</hi> asking,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. If ſuch a ſuit be triable in ſuch a Court<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Who are the adverſaries Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors? Who his Witneſſes? Who enjoined to him in a ſtrict tye of friendſhip? Who did, ſpake, writ this or that? Who is Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the controverted form?</item>
                  <item>3. What is exhibited in the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Declaration? What he thinketh they do now deliberate?</item>
                  <item>4. To what Mannour, the Farm in queſtion appertaineth?</item>
                  <item>5. To what caſe this is like?</item>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:41178:29"/>
                  <item>6. How far he hath proceeded in the buſineſs, and how far he is like, till the ſuit be determined?</item>
                  <item>7. Why he ſaid, or did ſuch a thing?</item>
                  <item>8. About what the controverſie chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dependeth?</item>
                  <item>9. How he muſt proceed in the cauſe?</item>
                  <item>10. What is the condition of the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges?</item>
                  <item>11. How much coſt the drawing of the Reply or Declaration?</item>
                  <item>12. <hi>By</hi> what means the poſſeſſion was regained?</item>
               </list>
               <p>The moſt material paſſages in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending cauſe, may be inveſtigated by propounding ſuch like queſtions: I hope no man will repent his labour in commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe lines to <hi>Memory,</hi> whereby he may reap ſo much benefit in his ſtudies and common affairs.</p>
               <p>Whereas I firſt made mention of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite Argument, I ſhall entreat the Readers patience, whileſt I declare the cauſe thereof, not finding any ſufficient Reaſon to baniſh or expel an Indefinite Argument out of the Logical Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and admire that <hi>Ramus</hi> hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted it: I think (reſerving place for better Judgment) an argument abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41178:29"/>conſentaneous, is branched more arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially in this manner.</p>
               <p>An argument abſolutely conſentane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, is <hi>indefinite,</hi> or <hi>definite; indefinite</hi> is that which argueth a thing indefinitely, as, <hi>God is. There is a fift Eſſence; Definite</hi> is that which argueth a thing definitely: <hi>Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> is the cauſe and effect.</p>
               <p>Now in this axiome <hi>(God is)</hi> we do not affirm that God is this or that, but ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that he is: And when we ſay <hi>(there is a fift Eſſence in rerum natura)</hi> we do not ſhew what cauſes it hath, or what effects, ſubjects or adjuncts, onely indefinitely pronounce, there is ſuch a thing. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, it is manifeſt, that an indefinite ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is ſufficiently diſtinguiſhed from all other arguments, becauſe it doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly anſwer this peculiar queſtion <hi>(If it be?)</hi> which yeildeth very profitable uſe in Diſcourſe: This by the way.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, In this way of remembring by Verſes formerly excogitated, both the parts, <hi>Repoſition</hi> and <hi>Depoſition,</hi> are diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in like manner as before; for like as by one repetition of the Verſes we charge the memory; ſo by another we diſcharge it: Whence there is no need here of any Rules of <hi>Revocation,</hi> ſeeing that if the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41178:30"/>Verſes be once firmly fixed in memory, no part of them will be to ſeek.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice for the firſt <hi>Poetical</hi> way of remembring, that is by Verſes provided before-hand: Now I will paſs to the next way of <hi>Remembring</hi> by extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary Verſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III: <hi>Of remembring by</hi> ex tempore <hi>Verſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis order of remembring by <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary</hi> Verſes, is when the occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſubjects to be remembred, are diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Verſe, in the ſame order as they preſent themſelves; by repetition of which they are again recalled to mind: Firſt, I will handle how to charge the memory <hi>ex tempore,</hi> afterward I will propound the Depoſition or diſcharging of things ſo committed to mind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Extemporary Repoſition</hi> is, when many ſentences are delivered in cuſtody to the mind, by certain eſſential words interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in Meeter, and often repeated; in which caſe great care muſt be uſed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print the firſt Letter of each portion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41178:30"/>perfectly in memory. For example, ſuppoſe in a Sermon preached in your hearing, you do principally obſerve theſe Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which you would preſerve in mind, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Earth digged out of a Well, how deep ſoever, expoſed to the air upon a high Tower, although it ſeemeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain no Seed of Herbs, neither is ſown by man, yet of its own accord produceth green Herbs; Whence is proved, That there is an innate faculty in every part of the Earth to germinate, infuſed by God thereinto in the Creation, by his Word, <hi>Let the earth bud,</hi> &amp;c.<hi>Gen.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is better to doubt of ſecret things, then to ſtrive about ſuch as are uncertain, <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The birth of God is to be ſilently adored, not buſily pried into. <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Not to ſin is God's Righteouſneſs; man's Righteouſneſs is God's Indulgence. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Magiſtracy cannot compel to Faith and Religion; but may and ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain to the means of Faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:41178:31"/> 6. The folly of School-men is ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, not unlike <hi>Mahomets</hi> Dreams, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that the place of Terreſtrial Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe was elevated many degrees above the Earth level, when as Paradiſe was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly defaced by the Deluge, if not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p n="7">7. He who moderateth himſelf in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful things, never falleth into unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In natural and civil actions, man doth yet retain free-will; but in ſpiritual and ſuper-natural he lyeth in a dead-ſleep til he be vivified by infuſion of Chriſt's Grace.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In ſacred Baptiſm, the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of great efficacy; but the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator of ſmall.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Miſſa,</hi> whence cometh the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Word <hi>Maſſe,</hi> of the ſame ſignification, denoted no more primarily, then <hi>Miſſio,</hi> like as <hi>Remiſſa</hi> is the ſame as <hi>Remiſsio,</hi> and <hi>Offenſa</hi> as <hi>Offenſio:</hi> It is certain, the original thereof was derived from a cuſtom among the Fathers living in the primive times, of celebrating the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> alwayes after publike prayers, and reading and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Scriptures; at which Novices in the faith, perſons unbaptized and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41178:31"/>might not be preſent, though they had all permiſſion to attend at Prayers and Sermons. Therefore a Decree was made, that they which did not communicate of the Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> ſhould be diſmiſſed before the Celebration. <hi>Coun. Carthage,</hi> 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 8. Whence <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Sermon of Time, 237. ſaith, <hi>Behold after Sermon, diſmiſsion is pronounced to ſuch as are not ſufficiently inſtructed in Chriſtian Religion; the faithful ſtays.</hi> Hence it is manifeſt, the Papiſtical Maſs is far different from that of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for neither do the Prieſts diſmiſs thoſe who do not communicate, but do not ſomtimes admit any to the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Wherefore he ſaith, Riſe up thou which ſleepeſt, ſtand up from the dead, and Chriſt will give thee light.</hi> By the firſt clauſe of this verſe <hi>(wherefore he ſaith)</hi> ſeems to be implied, that <hi>Paul</hi> did not pronounce this ſentence of his own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but cited it from ſome other place; yet ſeeing this ſentence is no where read in Scripture, it is probable that <hi>Paul</hi> doth here introduce Chriſt, ſpeaking by his Apoſtles in their ordinary Goſpel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, ſaying, <hi>Riſe up thou which ſleepeſt, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe words are daily pronounced <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:41178:32"/>
                  <hi>Reg.</hi> 1. If any portion of a Sentence negligently committed to memory, be loſt in depoſition, you muſt try if it may be recovered out of oblivion, by the number of ſyllables of which ſuch por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did conſiſt; for the number of the ſyllables will either bring it to light, or inſtruct yee to conjecture probably what it was. For example, in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Poetical Repoſition, delivered in the former Chapter, ſuppoſe that the ſecond portion of the ſecond Verſe be forgotten, the firſt and third portions being theſe:</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Not to ſin</hi>—<hi>Paradiſe on Earth.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>By numbering the ſyllables of theſe two known portions, the middle-porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is found to conſiſt of four ſyllables; which conſideration alone may happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recall the latent portion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reg.</hi> 2. If this way fail, bend your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to finde out the firſt Letter of the ſame, repeating the Letters of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet in order, taking good heed which your mind doth ſuggeſt to have been the firſt Letter, wherein your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory will certainly prompt you, unleſs you were very remiſs and negligent in charging the ſame: The firſt Letter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41178:32"/>found, the reſt unknown, you muſt apply that ſeverally to every Letter of the Alphabet, becauſe your mind will likewiſe acquieſce, when you come to that which was the ſecond. Thus having reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the two firſt Letters of the elapſed portion, though the reſt be unknown, they may be eaſily enquired out by help of a Dictionary: As in the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, running ſpeedily over the words beginning with <hi>Un,</hi> you will ſoon meet with <hi>unconſtrained,</hi> which was the firſt word of the loſt portion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reg.</hi> 3. If you cannot attain to the ſame this way, you muſt compare the parts placed on either ſide (if the latent ſentence were any part of a continued Sermon compoſed methodically) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your ſelf how the Speaker paſſed from the precedent to the ſubſequent; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if a man remember the fourth and ſixth obſervations of a late-heard Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, diſpoſed in good method, he may regain the fifth, lying as it were in the way, with little or no trouble, by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the method, how he deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the fifth to the ſixth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reg.</hi> 4. If ſtill you remain unreſolved, take in hand the indagation of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41178:33"/>and form thereof; By matter, I mean the ſubject of the ſentence in queſt; by form, I underſtand the ſtructure thereof <hi>(Conſcience is a natural faculty of the mind, placed in the ſupremeſt part thereof, aſſenting to good, diſallowing evil, and therefore of it ſelf never ſinneth)</hi> the <hi>matter</hi> of this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is <hi>Conſcience,</hi> the <hi>form,</hi> the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Matter</hi> of a ſentence be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in Oblivion, then the more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Claſſes</hi> of common places are to be leiſurely peruſed, poſſibly when you come at the right head, the mind demurring there, may produce the whole Sentence, or at leaſt, the matter thereof will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſelf. The more general Heads or Claſſes (in my Opinion) are theſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Of God in general.</item>
                  <item>Of the Trinity.</item>
                  <item>Of the Holy Ghoſt.</item>
                  <item>Of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>Of the Counſel of God.</item>
                  <item>Of the Creation.</item>
                  <item>Of God's Providence.</item>
                  <item>Of the World.</item>
                  <item>Of Time.</item>
                  <item>Of Angels.</item>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:41178:33"/>
                  <item>Of Devils.</item>
                  <item>Of man in general.</item>
                  <item>Of godly men.</item>
                  <item>Of wicked men.</item>
                  <item>Of brutiſh Creatures.</item>
                  <item>Of inſenſible Creatures.</item>
                  <item>Of the bleſſings of this life.</item>
                  <item>Of the affliction of this life</item>
                  <item>Of Duties.</item>
                  <item>Of ſin.</item>
                  <item>Of indifferent things.</item>
                  <item>Of Houſhold Government.</item>
                  <item>Of Policy.</item>
                  <item>Of the Church in general.</item>
                  <item>Of the typical Church.</item>
                  <item>Of the Evangelical Church.</item>
                  <item>Of the Word of God.</item>
                  <item>Of Sacraments.</item>
                  <item>Of Hereſies.</item>
                  <item>Of the end of the World.</item>
                  <item>Of eternal Life.</item>
                  <item>Of eternal Death.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In like manner to find out the latent form, the formal words included in this <hi>Hemiſtick,</hi> are to be rehearſed, which do naturally ſhew the form of any Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41178:34"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Not, Some, Or, Though, Therefore, Like as, If, None, And, All.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That theſe words, or their Synony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes, do ſhew the formal manner of all ſentences, may thus appear.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Negative, The Note whereof is, Not,</item>
                  <item>Particular, The Note whereof is, Some,</item>
                  <item>Disjunctive, The Note whereof is, Or,</item>
                  <item>Diſcretive, The Note whereof is, Though,</item>
                  <item>Illative, The Note whereof is, Therefore,</item>
                  <item>Relative, The Note whereof is, Like as,</item>
                  <item>Conditional, The Note whereof is, If,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>General Negative</hi> The Note whereof is, None,</item>
                  <item>Copulative, The Note whereof is, And,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>General Affirmative,</hi> The Note whereof is, All.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>If,</hi> the Matter being found, the form be ſtill wanting, then apply the Matter of the Sentence leiſurely to all Logical pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, enquiring firſt <hi>if it be?</hi> in the next place, <hi>What are the efficient cauſes, matter, form, end, ſubjects, adjuncts thereof, &amp;c.</hi> So may you extort it, though it were dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant in the Brains remoteſt Cell, or drowned in the River <hi>Lethe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, If the Sentence ſought for, cannot be diſcovered by any of theſe ways, let it paſs, and deſpair not of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41178:34"/>it; for though now it be concealed, when you ſeek it; yet if that portion of the ſentence comprehended in your verſe, be read or heard any where, that ſame, or the next day, it is a hundred to one but the whole ſentence will preſent it ſelf to mind.</p>
               <p>Here we will conclude the manner of Remembring by extemporary Verſes, which ſeemeth principally referred to them, who imploy their ſtudy much in Poetry, and are indued with a good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morative faculty. Thus much may alſo ſuffice for the Poetical Art of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring: Now let us paſs to the method of remembring by <hi>Idea's,</hi> which quickeneth even the dulleſt memories.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the Second Book.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41178:35"/>
            <head>The Art of Memory. The third Book.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of Repoſitories.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Art of <hi>Memory,</hi> which we now treat of conſiſteth of <hi>Ideas,</hi> and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein we will firſt handle the <hi>Repoſition of Idea's,</hi> and afterward their <hi>Depoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repoſition</hi> of <hi>Idea's</hi> is, when things to be remembred, are charged upon <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> by <hi>Idea's,</hi> diſpoſed in certain pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> but before I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to the manner of <hi>Repoſition,</hi> it is neceſſary for better explanation, to ſpeak of <hi>Repoſitories, Places,</hi> and <hi>Idea's</hi> in diſtinct chapters.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Repoſitory</hi> is an imaginary fabrick, fancied Artificially, built of hewen ſtone, in form of a <hi>Theater,</hi> the form whereof followeth; ſuppoſe the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to be twelve yards in length within the walls, in breadth ſix yards,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41178:35"/>and in height ſeven yards, the roof thereof flat, leaded above, and parget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted underneath, lying wholly open to view, without any wall on that ſide ſuppoſed next us: Let there be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined a <hi>Stage</hi> of ſmooth gray Marble, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and variegated with a party co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured border, which <hi>Stage</hi> is to be extended over the whole length and breadth of the building, and raiſed a yard high above the <hi>Level</hi> of the ground on which the ſaid Edifice is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected: Let all the walls, that is, the oppoſite wall, &amp; two ends be wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcotted with <hi>Cypreſſe</hi> beards, ſo artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally plained and glewed, that the joynts be indiſcernable; ſuppoſe alſo a <hi>Groove</hi> or <hi>Gutter</hi> cut in the middle of the <hi>Marble Stage,</hi> three inches broad, extended from the oppoſite wall to the hither ſide of the <hi>Stage,</hi> whereby it is exactly divided into two equall parts, and that upon the further end of the ſaid <hi>Groove,</hi> there is erreared a <hi>Column,</hi> a foot and half thick, ariſing up to the <hi>Roof</hi> of the building, almoſt touching the oppoſite wall, and deviding it into two equal parts, as the <hi>Groove</hi> divideth the <hi>Stage;</hi> ſo that by the <hi>Groove,</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41178:36"/>the <hi>Pillar,</hi> the whole <hi>Repoſitory</hi> is parted in twain, and conſiſteth of two <hi>Rooms,</hi> ſiding each other, each of them being ſix yards long, ſix yards broad, and ſix yards high. For the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this invention, I have cauſed a <hi>Type</hi> of the <hi>Repoſitory</hi> to be here deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neated, the explanation whereof im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately followeth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:41178:36"/>
               <figure/>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41178:37"/>
               <p> The Letters, <hi>a, b, c, d,</hi> ſhew the length of the Edifice, <hi>a, c, b, d,</hi> the height, <hi>a, e, b, f,</hi> the height of the <hi>Stage, g, i, k, h,</hi> are boundaries of the oppoſite wall, <hi>e, c, i, g,</hi> the ſide wall upon the left hand, <hi>h, k, d, f,</hi> the ſide wall of the right hand, <hi>c, l, m, d,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the <hi>Roof, g, i, n, p,</hi> the oppoſite wall of the firſt <hi>Room, e, g, o, p,</hi> the <hi>Stage</hi> of the firſt <hi>Room, r, q, k, h,</hi> the oppoſite wall of the ſecond <hi>Room, ſ, r, h, f,</hi> the <hi>Stage</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Room, n, o,</hi> the <hi>Pillar</hi> dividing the oppoſite wall, <hi>o<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p,</hi> the <hi>Groove</hi> wrought into the <hi>Stage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Repoſitory</hi> according to this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, is to be repreſented before the eyes of our minde, whereſoever we are, as oft as we intend to practiſe this Art; ſuppoſing our ſelves to ſtand about two yards diſtant, againſt the midſt thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41178:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of Places.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A <hi>Place</hi> (as to our conſideration) is an apt ſpace in a <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for reception of <hi>Idea's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are onely two <hi>Places</hi> in every <hi>Repoſitory</hi> of equal form and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that is the two rooms of each <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory</hi> determinated as a foreſaid by the <hi>Pillar</hi> and <hi>Groove.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That place is ſaid to be the former, which is on the right hand of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory,</hi> that which is on the left hand, the latter; That part of the <hi>Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> is ſaid to be on the right hand, which is oppoſite to the left hand of a man ſtanding againſt the middle of the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> that on the left hand which is oppoſite to the right.</p>
               <p>Thus in the <hi>Scheme</hi> exhibited in the former Chapter, the letters, <hi>g, i, n, o,</hi> demonſtrate the oppoſite wall of the right hand part, or firſt place or <hi>room</hi> of the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> and the letters, <hi>e, g, o, p,</hi> the <hi>Stage</hi> thereof; ſo <hi>r, q, k, h,</hi> are Indices of the oppoſite wall of the left hand part, or ſecond <hi>Place</hi> or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41178:38"/>
                  <hi>room</hi> of the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> and <hi>ſ, r, h, f,</hi> the <hi>Stage</hi> of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of</hi> Idea's <hi>in General.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AN <hi>Idea</hi> is a viſible repreſentation of things to be <hi>remembred,</hi> fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a ſtrong imagination, by help whereof the minde by reflexion cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to <hi>memory,</hi> together with the <hi>Idea,</hi> the thing repreſented. <hi>Idea's</hi> are to be veſted with their proper circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, according as their natures require, for like as <hi>Writings,</hi> the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they are, are more facilly read; ſo <hi>Idea's,</hi> the more aptly they are conceived, according to the exigency of their nature, are more ſpeedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called to minde; and alſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the things by them ſignified. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is to be attributed to <hi>Idea's</hi> of move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able things; <hi>quiet</hi> to <hi>Idea's</hi> of quiet things, and good or evil ſavours, to <hi>Ideas</hi> repreſenting things ſo qualified. Examples of moveable <hi>Idea's,</hi> are Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers at work in their ſhops, women
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41178:38"/>dauncing, Trees ſhaken by the wind, Water running from Cocks, and ſuch like. <hi>Idea's</hi> of quiet things, are Henns laying in their neſts, Thieves lurking under buſhes, <hi>&amp;c. Idea's</hi> to which ſound is aſcribed, are a Lion roaring, a Bell ringing, whiſtling, murmure of Trees, a Quiriſter ſinging, a Huntſman hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Moreover, if Perfume, burning in a Chafing-diſh, be uſed for an <hi>Idea,</hi> a ſweet and pleaſant odour muſt be attributed thereto, on the contrary to vaults under ground, a filthy, unwholſome ſtink, is to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned; ſo <hi>Idea's</hi> of merry men, require cheerfulneſs of countenance, of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, pale-neſſe and ſadneſſe. After this manner <hi>Idea's</hi> sot Edifices, Machines, and all Artificial things whatſoever, ought to be ſignaliſed; proportion of form, and ſplendour of colours, muſt be attributed to <hi>Pictures,</hi> grace and livelineſſe of Letters, to <hi>Writings,</hi> glory and excellency of <hi>Wormanſhip,</hi> to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravings,;</hi> Finally, every <hi>Idea</hi> muſt have ſuch illuſtration as may render it moſt notable and conſpicuous, and ſeem principally coherent to its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41178:39"/>
               <p> But before I proceed further, it is expedient to take into conſideration, the common <hi>Affection</hi> of <hi>Ideas,</hi> their <hi>Species,</hi> ſhall ſucceed after, in a more proper place.</p>
               <p>The common <hi>Affections</hi> of <hi>Idea's</hi> are three: <hi>Quantity, Poſition,</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Quantitie of <hi>Idea's.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AN <hi>Idea</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Quantity,</hi> is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>equal, greater,</hi> or <hi>leſſer</hi> then the thing repreſented.</p>
               <p>An equal <hi>Idea</hi> is, when the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, is beſtowed in a <hi>Place</hi> of the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> in its proper and due magnitude, as being neither too great to be contained therein, nor ſo ſmall it cannot be diſcerned by one ſtanding before the <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> ſuch are <hi>Chairs, Pictures, Tables, Beds, Heaps of Stone, Piles of Wood, two Combatants in a ſingle Duel,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>An-augmented, or greater <hi>Idea,</hi> is when the thing to be remembred, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41178:39"/>to a multitude, that it may be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter viewed at a diſtance, which elſe being ſmall, would not fall under cognizance; as if the thing to be depoſited in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory,</hi> were a <hi>Penny,</hi> a <hi>Pearl,</hi> a Grain of <hi>Muſtard-Seed,</hi> or a <hi>Spider,</hi> which are ſo ſmall, that diſpoſed in a Room of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory,</hi> they eſcape the ſight of a man ſtanding before the <hi>Repoſitory:</hi> In ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, inſtead of one Penny, imagine a heap of Pence new coined; Inſtead of one Pearl, a multitude of Pearls; Inſtead of one Grain of Muſtard-ſeed, fancy certain Buſhels ſcattered about the Stage; And for one Spider, ſuppoſe a multitude creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the oppoſite Wall.</p>
               <p>A contracted or leſſer <hi>Idea</hi> is, when the thing to be remembred is ſo great, that it cannot be comprehended in its proper natural quantity, within ſuch narrow li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits as a room of a <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> &amp; is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore imagined to be pourtrayed with ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant lively colours, in a Picture fixed to the oppoſite Wall. Thus ſpace of places how far ſoever diſtant, &amp; all great things, may be facilely repreſented in a Picture: As if the thing to be remembred were a Battel, a triumphant ſpectacle, hunting or hawking through Woods and Groves,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41178:40"/>a Naval conflict, large Territories, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, a Mountain, or Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whoſe <hi>Idea's</hi> cannot be contained in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial places, unleſs contracted, and aptly and artificially comprized in a Picture, conceited by imagination hanging againſt the oppoſite Wall, that ſo it may be fully comprehended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Poſition of</hi> Idea's.</head>
               <p>LEt the Poſition of every <hi>Idea</hi> be ſuch as in vulgar uſe doth moſt commonly appertain to the thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified; Let the <hi>Idea's</hi> of things uſually hanged againſt a Wall, be ſo diſpoſed in the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> as Muſical Inſtruments, Arms, Looking-Glaſſes, Pictures, Bruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, written Tables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such things as are cuſtomarily faſtened to, or in a Wall, imagine them accommodated in the Repoſitory in like manner, as Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-pages of Books paſted againſt the Pillar, Proclamations, or printed pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges nailed to the Wall, Funeral-Strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, or Pendants, in the higher part
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41178:40"/>of the oppoſite Wall, as you ſee in Churches: Such things as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſet upon ſhelves, fancy them ſo placed in the Repoſitory, as Veſſels of Gold, Silver, Glaſſes, Books, Mercery Wares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such things as are uſually placed on a Table, conceive them ſo marſhalled in the Repoſitory, as Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, Sums of Money, Table-Boards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch things as lye, or are any ways ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate on ground, muſt be ſo placed in the <hi>Reyoſitory,</hi> as heaps of Wheat, a Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, Cheſt, Table, living Creatures, whether ſtanding, fitting, or lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such things as are frequently under ground, are to be ſuppoſed under the Marble-Stage; for though they eſcape the eye of a man ſtanding before the Repoſitory, yet they cannot be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the eyes of his mind, which are onely exerciſed in this matter; of this ſort are Graves, Wells, Wine-Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, Mettaline-Mines, Subterranean paſſages, through which ſtreams have their courſe, as Blood in the Veins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Like method is to be obſerved in ſite and poſition of all other things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41178:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the Colours of</hi> Repoſitories <hi>and</hi> Idea's.</head>
               <p>HEre you are to be admoniſhed, that though every <hi>Repoſitory</hi> is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be uniform in Building; yet they are diſtinguiſhed from one another by the pillar in the middle of every <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory,</hi> which muſt be imagined of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral colours; as if you uſe ten, that which you deſign for the firſt, muſt be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have a Golden Pillar; the ſecond a Pillar of Silver: the third of black ſtone; the fourth of blew ſtone; the fift of red ſtone; the ſixth of yellow ſtone; the ſevench of green ſtone; the eighth of purple ſtone, the ninth of white ſtone, the tenth of Cinamon colour. Now for diſtinction ſake, Gold is called the colour of the firſt <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> Silver the colour of the ſecond <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> black of the third <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> and ſo ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as before. If you uſe more than ten Repoſitories, you muſt repeat the ſame colours over again, as before; ſo that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41178:41"/>the eleventh is imagined to have a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den pillar, the twelfth a ſilver pillar, the thirteenth a black pillar, the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth a blew pillar, and ſo the reſt in order. After the ſame manner every <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> muſt be conceived cloathed, adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ſome way illuſtrated with the proper colour of the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is imagined to be placed. Take an example or two for better explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Suppoſe a Saylor in a Canvaſe Suit be retained for an <hi>Idea</hi> in the firſt <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory,</hi> I repreſent him ſtanding there with a Golden Chain over his ſhoulder like a Belt; if in the ſecond, imagine he weareth a ſilver Chain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his neck, with a Whittle faſtened thereto: If in the third, that he hath black Boots on his legs: If in the fourth, that he hath a blew Skarf on his Arm, tyed in a roſe-knot: If in the fifth, that he wears a Red Monmouth Cap on his head: If in the ſixth, that he ſwagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with a yellow Feather in his Cap: If in the ſeventh, that he hath a Green Silk Garter on his right leg: If in the eighth, that his Canvaſe Coat is imbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with a border of Purple Velvet: If in the ninth, that his neck is beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41178:42"/>with a very white Orient Pearl; If in the tenth, that he hath a pair of Cinnamon coloured Breeches.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, if the <hi>Idea</hi> of its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be any ways related to the colour of its <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> whereby it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently underſtood to have the colour thereof, it will need no other attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For example, if a Mayor of a City, (who in regard of his Office is dignified with a purple Gown, and Gold Chain) be placed as an Idea in the firſt or fift <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> there will be no need of Attribution of colour, becauſe the Golden Chain doth manifeſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the colour of the firſt <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> the purple Gown the colour of the fift. In like ſort, if a black Bull be placed as an Idea in either room of the firſt <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory,</hi> his horns muſt be conceived gild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Gold; if in the ſecond, with ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; if in the third, black, being the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per colour of that <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> excludeth any other addition: If in the fourth, let him be decked with a Chaplet of blew Flowers; if in the fift, with a Garland of red Roſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So a Picture imagined to be painted on the oppoſite Wall of the firſt <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> muſt be illuſtrated with
<pb facs="tcp:41178:42"/>Gold in ſome convenient place: If in the oppoſite Wall of the ſecond <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> with ſilver; of the third, with black, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This attribution of a <hi>Repoſitories</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, is of marvellous uſe, both to keep in mind the <hi>Idea's</hi> themſelves, as alſo their order; hereby the mind re-peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Idea's</hi> formerly beſtowed, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſome certainty to guide it ſelf, and recollect any <hi>Idea</hi> at preſent latent; becauſe it's unqueſtionable, that the miſſing <hi>Idea</hi> is either wholly, or at leaſt in part, illuſtrated with the proper co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of its <hi>Repoſitory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, in attributing a <hi>Repoſitories</hi> colour to an <hi>Idea,</hi> (of it ſelf not parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof) you muſt be careful that the colour of the <hi>Repoſitory</hi> be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to the moſt eminent part of the <hi>Idea,</hi> or as near as may be: If the Hiſtory of the Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi> thrown into the Sea by Mariners, be uſed as an <hi>Idea,</hi> it muſt be repreſented in a picture according to the third Chapter prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; in which, though the Whale, Sea, Ship &amp; Land are to be pourtrayed, yet the Effigies of <hi>Jonah</hi> himſelf is the moſt remarkable part of the picture, becauſe <hi>Jonah</hi> is of the Hiſtory there painted: If
<pb facs="tcp:41178:43"/>therefore this Story be to be depoſited in the firſt <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> let the border of his Gown be ſuppoſed of Gold; if in the ſecond, of Silver; if in the third, let the Gown be fancyed black; if in the fourth, blew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo the top of a heap of Wheat is the moſt conſpicuous part; therefore if a heap of Wheat be placed in the firſt <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> imagine a Golden Streamer two foot long fixed in the top of the Heap; if in the ſecond <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> let the Streamer be Silver; if in the third, black; if in the fourth, blew, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus much may ſuffice for common Affections of <hi>Idea's,</hi> in quantity, poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and colour; their ſpecies follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Direct</hi> Idea's.</head>
               <p>AN <hi>Idea</hi> is ſimple or compound: A ſimple <hi>Idea</hi> is uniform, and is fourfold, <hi>direct, relative, fictitious</hi> and <hi>written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Direct Idea</hi> is when a viſible thing, or conceived under a viſible form, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> according to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41178:43"/>the ſame form, under which it is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally apprehended: So a <hi>Goat</hi> is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Idea of a <hi>Goat;</hi> a <hi>Rhinocerot</hi> of a <hi>Rhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocerot;</hi> a <hi>Peacock</hi> of a <hi>Peacock;</hi> a <hi>Dove</hi> of a <hi>Dove.</hi> Thus a Majeſtical man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with a Scepter, Imperial Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem and Robe, is the <hi>Idea</hi> of a King: A perſon arrayed in Academical habit, of a Schollar; An ancient woman in mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning weeds, weeping and wiping her face with an Handkerchief, of a widow: A Virgin apparelled like a Nun, of a Nun: A Satyr, as the Poets deſcribe them, of a Satyr: So a Temple is the direct Idea of a Temple, a Book of a Booke, a Bed of a Bed, a Sheath of a Sheath, an Image of an Image<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a picture of a picture, an Epiſtle of an Epiſtle, a Bond ſealed, of a Bond: So good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Spirits, though they be incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal and inviſible, (ſeeing they are commonly conceived under viſible forms) may be repoſited as the other. To conclude, the minde of man doth naturally &amp; immediately preſent direct <hi>Idea's</hi> of all viſible things, or ſuch as are conceived under a viſible form, that it is in vain to excogitate any, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life thoſe that offer themſelves. If
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41178:44"/>a man hears the relation of a Naval Battel, doth not he preſently ſeem to behold the Sea, Ships, ſmoke of great, Ordnance, and other things obvious in ſuch matters. If ſpeech be made of muttering an Army, doth not the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer form in his minde the Effigies of a Field, repleniſhed with Souldiers mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in Military poſtures. No precept in this kind is delivered, which Nature it ſelf hath not dictated; but onely to imprint theſe <hi>Idea</hi>'s more deeply in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, we beſtow them methodically in ſome place, left otherwiſe they be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten through light apprehenſion. To explain this more evidently, I will uſe an example.</p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>An Example of remembering a Hiſtory.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Cynick</hi> entering <hi>Plato</hi>'s Hall, when he ſaw the Table covered with a rich Carpet, the Shelves glitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Silver, Gilt Cups, Veſſels, and other ſumptuous furniture, laid hold of the Carpet with all his might, threw it to the ground, and trod thereon with his feet, ſaying, <hi>I tread upon</hi> Plato's <hi>pride:</hi> To whom <hi>Plato</hi> replied, <hi>But with greater pride:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:41178:44"/>
                  <p> The <hi>Idea</hi> of this Story is not ſo great, but that it may admit Repoſition in its equal quantity: Therefore I ſuppoſe in the place of the <hi>Repoſitory</hi> where it is to be beſtowed, that there is a table cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a rich Carpet, which a ſordid fellow in beggarly Raiment, throws on the ground, a grave man clothed in honeſt ſober apparel looking on. The attribution of the colour of the <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory</hi> is not to be forgotten: If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be the firſt <hi>Repoſitory</hi> in which this <hi>Idea</hi> is to be placed, I imagine the Carpet to be imbelliſhed with a fringe or border of God: If in the ſecond, of Silver: If in the third, of black: If in the fourth, of blew, and ſo forth in the reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another Example.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When</hi> Caius Julius Ceſar firſt <hi>invaded</hi> Britain, <hi>the inhabitants taking arms ſet upon him, and in ſet-battel drave him and his old Souldiers to flight:</hi> Whence that of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> concerning <hi>Caeſars</hi> repulſe.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Territa quaeſitis oftendit terga Britanis.</l>
                     <l>Unto the Britains found, afrighted backs he ſhew'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:41178:45"/>
                  <p> The <hi>Idea</hi> of this hiſtory muſt be contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe it cannot be contained in the memorial place in its due magnitude, <hi>C.</hi> 4. Therefore I imagine the repreſentation of a ſharp Battel, fairly interwoven in the hangings, doth cover the half portion of the oppoſite Wall, either on the right or left hand, not omitting the fit attribution of the <hi>Repoſitories</hi> colour; wherein one part of the Combatants perſonating the <hi>Romans,</hi> are armed and clad more ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy, their General and Standard-Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, with their whole Squadron, giving ground, whereby their fellows take an occaſion of flight; the other part, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning the <hi>Britains,</hi> in more rude and Savage attire, preſs their flying Enemies, and proſecute their victory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>An example of a Sentence to be remembred, the Subject being viſible.</head>
                  <p>An <hi>Ant</hi> is a ſmall Inſect, the coldeſt and dryeſt of all Creatures, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wiſeſt; for cold and dry do chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribute to Wiſdom. The <hi>Idea</hi> of this ſentence ought to be augmented; for the magnitude of an <hi>Ant</hi> is ſo inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that being beſtowed in a memorial
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41178:45"/>place, it eſcapeth ſight: Therefore I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an <hi>Ant</hi>-heap in the middle ſtage of the memorial place, ſeeming almoſt black with <hi>Ants,</hi> ſwarming hither and thither; As for aſſignation of colour if this <hi>Idea</hi> be placed in the third <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> is ſufficiently no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the blackneſs of the <hi>Ants;</hi> if in the ſeventh, by the greenneſs of the <hi>Ant</hi>-hill; ſo that there needeth no addition of colour, if placed in the third or ſeventh Repoſitory: But if it be deſigned to the firſt Repoſitory, let a Triangular Golden Streamer be ſuppoſed fixed in the <hi>Ant</hi>-hill, a foot high; if in the ſecond, a Silver Streamer; if in the fourth, a Streamer of blew Silk; if in the fifth, of red; if in the ſixt, of yellow; if in the eighth, of purple; if in the ninth, of white; if in the tenth, of Cinnamon colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another Example.</head>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q>
                  <p>Or as <hi>Ovid</hi> hath it in his firſt Book <hi>De Amore:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Qnid magis eſt durum ſaxo? quid molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us unda?</l>
                     <l>Dura tamen molli ſaxa cavantur aqua.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:41178:46"/>
                     <l>What is harder then a ſtone? then water ſoft?</l>
                     <l>Yet Stones are worn by Water dropping oft.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Either ſentence ſignifying the ſame thing, are diſpoſed after a like manner, by ſuppoſing a Leaden Spout, ſuſtained by an Iron Prop, faſtened in the upper part of the oppoſite Wall of the Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, doth diſcharge plenty of water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Marble Stage, which is worn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath with the continual drip: In this caſe the prop of the Spout may exhibit the colour of the Repoſitory.</p>
                  <p>All Hiſtories, Actions, Fables, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Affairs; all viſible things, or concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under a viſible form; finally. All ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences whoſe ſubject is viſible , may be diſpoſed in Repoſitories by Direct Ideas, in equal, augmented or contracted quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Relative Ideas.</head>
               <p>A Simple <hi>relative Idea</hi> is, when ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be rememembred is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by his <hi>Correlative.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:41178:46"/>
               <p> Firſt, when the Cauſe is ſignified by the <hi>effect,</hi> as <hi>Melancholy</hi> by a ſad man, with his hat pulled over his eyes, his arms folded a croſs, his eies looking on the ground, ſtanding immoveable: The <hi>Spring</hi> by <hi>Green Meadows</hi> and <hi>Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring trees: Winter</hi> by houſes, <hi>Plants, earth,</hi> and all other things covered with <hi>Snow,</hi> and rigid with <hi>Froſt: Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony</hi> by a <hi>Fat man,</hi> vomitting half di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted morſels.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when the <hi>effect</hi> is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as you did note the <hi>oppreſſion of the poor,</hi> by ſome eminent <hi>Oppreſſour,</hi> generally ſpoken againſt for his unjuſt accumulation of <hi>riches: bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy</hi> by ſome notorious <hi>blaſphemer,</hi> whoſe diſcourſe is frequently forced with impious oaths.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when the <hi>Subject</hi> is noted by an <hi>Adjunct,</hi> as <hi>Regal dignity,</hi> by a Scepter and Crown; a <hi>Tavern,</hi> by a Buſh; <hi>Exorciſme,</hi> by a Figure or charm; the <hi>Planets</hi> and twelve houſes, by their proper characters appropriated unto them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, when an <hi>Adjunct</hi> is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the <hi>Subject;</hi> as <hi>Cold,</hi> by <hi>Ice; heat,</hi> by <hi>fire; light,</hi> by a <hi>candle; love,</hi> by a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41178:47"/>
                  <hi>heart,</hi> the ſeat of affection; <hi>pride</hi> by a <hi>Peacok</hi> ſpreading his tail; <hi>Gluttony,</hi> by an <hi>Eſtrich; Drunkenneſſe,</hi> by a noted drunkard; <hi>Impudence,</hi> by a norious whore; <hi>Avarice</hi> by a rich man count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, when one like thing, is put for another, as <hi>Parallel Circles,</hi> for the world; <hi>a clean writing book<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> for a <hi>ſoule;</hi> a <hi>Serpent</hi> with a tail in his mouth, for a <hi>year,;</hi> a <hi>woman</hi> embracing a broken pillar, for <hi>Fortitude;</hi> a <hi>Virgine</hi> veiled, holding a drawn ſword in her right hand, &amp; a pair of ballances in her left, for <hi>Juſtice;</hi> a <hi>Winged old man,</hi> having long hair in the forepart of his head, bald behind, and holding a Sythe in his hand, for Time: A man lading wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of a pond with a Sive, for a fool undertaking an impoſible thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, When a ſentence is denoted by ſome particular example, by which the truth thereof is notably demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as, <hi>No Element is qualified with gravity in its proper place:</hi> This Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical axiome may be fitly illuſtrated by a man diving under water, who ſo long as he is in the Water, is not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that is ponderous, but out of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41178:47"/>water findeth exprimentally a pail full of water heavy: The quantity of ſuch Ideas is equal; for I imagine all the Stage of the Memorial place, where this Idea is to be repreſented, convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a Bath, with a capacious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ciſtern, a foot thick round about, filled to the brim with fair water, in the middle whereof a naked man ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth upright, lifting a Tankard of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with both his hands, as if he were ſhewing it: If this Idea be placed in the firſt <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> the Tankard muſt be ſuppoſed of Gold; if in the ſecond, of Silver; in the third, of Potters earth, black, in the fourth, blew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the <hi>Idea</hi> may be ſome way related to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of its place.</p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another Example.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The body heated with wine, boileth over with luſt.</hi> This Sentence may be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Lot,</hi> ſporting wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his two Daughters in the Grot, is a notable illuſtration thereof. To this purpoſe I imagine the Stage of the memorial place, wherein this Idea is to be conſerved, transformed into a Cave,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41178:48"/>as it were framed out of a natural Rock, and ſeem to behold <hi>Lot</hi> revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with his two Daughters: Here <hi>Lot's</hi> outer Garment muſt be deemed to bear the <hi>Repoſitories</hi> colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another Example.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Judicial Aſtrology</hi> is a buſie vanity. <hi>Baſil</hi> in <hi>Hexaemer. Hom.</hi> 1, This may be relatively fancied by the Hiſtory of <hi>Thales</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> about to take a Stars height with an <hi>Aſtrolobe</hi> in a clear night, who being ſomewhat heedleſs of his ſtation, fel into a Ditch, for which he was worthily derided of a Woman ſtanding by; becauſe he did ſo curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mind things over his head, he did neglect thoſe under his feet.</p>
                  <p>In brief, if any thing may be readily underſtood by its <hi>Correlative,</hi> the ſame maybe uſed for a <hi>Relative Idea;</hi> by which kind of <hi>Idea,</hi> all kind of <hi>Hyeroglyphicks</hi> and innumerable ſentences ingenuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exemplified, may be repofited in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitories.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:41178:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Fictitious</hi> Ideas.</head>
               <p>A ſimple <hi>Fictitious Idea,</hi> is when any thing is beſtowed by way of a ſubſtitute, wherewith it is faigned to have ſome ſuppoſed conveniency; as when a word of <hi>Homonymous</hi> ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, denoting ſome viſible thing in one ſenſe (either in our our own lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or another) is ſubſtituted for ſomething inviſible or unknown. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner proper names are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reſerved in <hi>Memory:</hi> as in Latine, <hi>Ramus,</hi> a mans name, may be ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>per ramum viridem,</hi> a green branch; <hi>Remus, per remum,</hi> an Oare; So in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, <hi>Smith</hi> a mans name, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a Smith blowing up fire in his Forge. <hi>Pinke,</hi> by the Flower ſo called: <hi>Carpenter,</hi> by one of that trade plaining boards: <hi>Penelope,</hi> by the Picture of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelope</hi> and her web: <hi>Lucrece,</hi> by the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the <hi>Roman</hi> Lady ſo called, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing her own death. Thus ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers names may be conſerved by
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41178:49"/>friends or acquaintance of the ſame name; as <hi>John</hi> a ſtrangers name, by a brother or friend, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; ſo <hi>Grace,</hi> ſignifying favour, may be retained by <hi>Grace,</hi> a womans name.</p>
               <p>Thus words or names (which at large ſignifie no viſible thing) which divided into parts, ſignifie one or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, may be laid up in <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> on the Stage, wall, or hangings in decent order; as theſe Barbarous words in Latine,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, ſis, ſus.</note> 
                  <hi>Apergliſſus,</hi> by a <hi>Clay banke,</hi> on the right hand whereof (which is towards our left hand) a <hi>Bear</hi> wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and on the left (toward our right hand) a <hi>Sow. Tedaſpis,</hi> by a <hi>Torch</hi> and an <hi>Asp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, aſpis. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Boſarnos,</hi> by an <hi>Oxe</hi> and a <hi>Lamb. Araphos,</hi> by an <hi>Altar</hi> and a <hi>Light.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Suſtineamus,</hi> by a <hi>Sow,</hi> a <hi>Moth,</hi> and a <hi>Mouſe,</hi> according to that noted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſe,</p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rfur edit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pannum, panem quoque ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineamus.</q>
               <q>Sow eats Bran, a Moth Cloth, a a Mouſe Bread.</q>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:41178:49"/>
               <p> So <hi>Coxcomb</hi> in Engliſh, may be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by two <hi>Cocks</hi> fighting, &amp; pulling each other by the <hi>Comb. Birdlington,</hi> by a <hi>Bird, Ling fiſh</hi> ſo called, and a <hi>Tunne. Harbottle,</hi> by a <hi>Hare</hi> and a <hi>Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Some men to fix ſingle words and letters more firmly in memory, uſe the images of men and women for ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuted <hi>Ideas</hi> of Letters, and for ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (to uſe their own phraſe) attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute actions to them, whereby the minde may be provoked to the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Mercy, Mirth, Luſt, Feare, Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, Wrath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſuch <hi>Ideas</hi> are by no means to be approved, Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is impious, and dangerons to cheriſh luſtfull or ſcurrulous images in the mind, which infect the ſoul, and render it more dull in performing its Office. Secondly, it wholly pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the natural manner of <hi>Remembring;</hi> for Nature teacheth men from their infancy, by the images of men, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend men, not letters, which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to infringe, is all one as to unteach Nature, which is both dangerous and difficult. Thirdly, too much time is loſt in animation of ſuch <hi>Ideas,</hi> which,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41178:50"/>is therefore done, that being revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Memory,</hi> they may be more deeply engraven. Laſtly, it is vain and altogether unprofitable, to frame an <hi>Alphabet</hi> of living Creatures, and learn them by heart, ſeeing they ſerve onely to apprehend naked Letters or ſingle words, whoſe uſe is not fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Written</hi> Idea's</head>
               <p>A Single written <hi>Idea,</hi> is when the thing to be <hi>Remembred,</hi> is imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be written with black letters in a plain white Table, four foot ſquare, hanging againſt the oppoſite wall of the <hi>Repoſitory.</hi> Written <hi>Idea's</hi> will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps at firſt ſeem too weak and infirm to prompt the <hi>Memory</hi> with any thing to be remembred; but if all our Rules which are required in diſpoſing writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Idea's,</hi> be ſtrictly obſerved, you will think otherwiſe.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:41178:50"/>
               <p> In every ſuch <hi>Idea,</hi> ſix things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Characters (ſuch as are Letters and Arithmetical figures) be ſuppoſed of ſuch magnitude, that they may be plainly read by one ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat remote; for ſo they are moſt eaſily attracted by the viſual fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and transferred to <hi>Memory,</hi> ſuch like writings and inſcriptions are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſeen in walls of Churches and houſes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That every <hi>Idea</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived written in the ſame form as are commonly expoſed in Books or Paper.</p>
               <p>In remembring Proofs, you muſt fancy the names of the Books abbrevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of names are diſtinguiſhed by their deſcent downward in order, as in the Alphabetical Catalogue of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aetians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Agnoites.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Albanenſes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anthropomorphiſts,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Apollinaries.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:41178:51"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Apellites.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Arrians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Artemonites.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Athelites,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Diſtribution of parts diſtinctly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, being referred to the whole, are thus explicated.</p>
               <p>Jewiſh feaſts have been
<list>
                     <item>more ſolemn, 3.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Paſsover.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Penticoſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Feaſt of Tab.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>leſs ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn, 3.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>New Moons,</hi> or <hi>of blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trumpet.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Feaſt of Expiation.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Feaſt of Dedication,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by <hi>Herod</hi> the Great.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>A Syllogiſme conſiſting of a <hi>Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Aſſumption,</hi> and <hi>Concluſion,</hi> is placed in divers diſtinct ſections, after this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He which devoureth things conſecrated to God, procureth deſtruction to his own family,</hi> Prov. 20.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But he which appropriated a portion of Glebe (pertaining to the Prieſt) to himſelf
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41178:51"/>and his heirs, devoureth that which is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate to God,</hi> Ezek. 45.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore he which appropriateth a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Glebe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Compariſon</hi> diſtributed into its two parts, hath <hi>Protaſis</hi> and <hi>Apodoſis</hi> collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally diſpoſed thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As there is great difference between the faculty of ſeeing, and the act of ſeeing; for the faculty is alwayes preſent, the act is often intermitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So there is great difference between the faculty of faith, and the act of believing: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate perſons after converſion, do alwayes poſſeſs the former, but the latter is often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So Poetical fragments are expreſſed in ſingle Verſes and Lines, long Sentences in proſe are deſcribed in Lines of equal length, ſummarily fancy all kind of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in their uſual mode.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is required, That you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Writing to begin at the upper end of the Table.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, One word at leaſt in every written Idea, muſt be very carefully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41178:52"/>and ſuppoſed to be expreſſed in Text-Letters, with all the Vowels in Gold, eſpecially let the firſt Letter be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, and the other tranſcendent Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, if there be any, drawn ſomewhat longer then cuſtomarily. Here you may obſerve, that of the ſmall Letters ſome are interlineary, ſome tranſcendents: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlineary letters in all kind of Writing, are ſuch as lye equally between two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel lines, as <hi>a, c, e, m, n, o, r, u, w.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tranſcendent letters are ſuch as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Interlineary ſpace, ſome of which do onely penetrate the upper line, as <hi>b, d, i, k, l, t, h,</hi> ſome the lower, as <hi>f, ſ, j.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, It is neceſſary, according to the Doctrine delivered in the ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that every Idea be rendered ſome way partaker of the colour of his <hi>Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory</hi>) that the frame or border of every Table be imagined of the ſame colour as his <hi>Repoſitory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, you muſt ſo long contemplate your ſuppoſed written Idea, till you have made at leaſt ſome ſmall impreſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in your memory, diligently obſerving in your mental meditation, the length of the whole; Writing the firſt letter of the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41178:52"/>principal word, as in the fourth Rule the Golden Vowels, tranſcendency and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the letters, with ſuch like conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as chiefly conduce to imprint the written Idea firmly in your imagination: For ſeeing Writings make leſs impreſſion in the mind, then things, they muſt be more carefully and longer revolved in mind, that they may accompliſh by aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity, what they cannot perform through imbecillity.</p>
               <p>Theſe generally required in every writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Idea, may ſuffice: Now I will deſcend to particular Rules; but conſidering that to treat of every particular kind of writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Idea, would be both laborious and unneceſſary, I will onely inſiſt upon the more uſual, which are four, a Word, a Proof, a Phraſe, a Sentence.</p>
               <p>A ſingle Word, and a Proof, cannot be ſuppoſed to have any principal Word, becauſe they be ſingular, which never the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs muſt be carefully taken notice of as in the fourth Rule.</p>
               <p>Let this Word <hi>(Spagyrus)</hi> be the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a Word to he imaginarily writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſignifying according to <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> one which can dexterouſly diſcern good
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:41178:53"/>from evil, truth from falſhood: Fancy the ſame thus written.</p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>SPAGYRUS.</head>
                  <p>In the Inſcription I diligently weigh the length of the Word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the firſt letter, the figure and order of the other letters, their colour and tranſcendency: Three are of Gold, <hi>a, y, u.</hi> three deſcend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the lower line, <hi>p, y, g.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the inſcription of a Proof, beſides the Name of the Book, the quantity of the Numbers is to be carefully obſerved: Number being the meaſure of quantity, and therefore meerly related to viſible things, is facilely kept in mind; the only obſervation of the quantity of Numbers, fixeth them perfectly in Memory. Take an Example of a Proof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.16</head>
                  <p>The letters <hi>e,</hi> and <hi>o,</hi> are fancied of Gold, <hi>x,</hi> and <hi>d,</hi> are tranſcendents, the former aſcending above the line, the latter deſcending beneath.</p>
                  <p>In writing a Phraſe and Sentence, the firſt Word is to be heedfully obſerved;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41178:53"/>and therefore the firſt letter muſt be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined very large, all the Vowels written with Gold, and the tranſcendents very largely extended, as is aforeſaid, <hi>Rul.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>Moreover in writing of Phraſes, all the Words except the firſt, muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed written with ſmall letters, after this manner.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To entice with flattering words.</l>
                     <l>Conceited with vain glorious bubbles.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>A Sentence conſiſteth of one or more clauſes.</p>
                  <p>A Sentence of one Clauſe may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed wholly written with Capital let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as,</p>
                  <p>NO CALAMITY IS ALONE. THE LAW OF GOD IS THE LIGHT OF MAN.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>FRIENDS HAVE ALL THINGS IN COMMON.</p>
                  <p>In Sentences of many Clauſes, you may ſuppoſe all the words of the firſt Clauſe marked with capital letters, the reſt with ſmall letters: As</p>
                  <p>SOLA SALUS SERVIRE Deo; <hi>ſunt coetera fraudes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:41178:54"/>
                  <p> GODS SERVICE IS CHIEFEST BLESSEDNESS; <hi>other things are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>QUANQUAM BONUM NON EST MALUM; eſt tamen bonum ut ſit malum.</hi> Auguſtine.</p>
                  <p>ALTHOUGH EVIL IS NOT GOOD; yet it is good that there ſhould be evil.</p>
                  <p>WHATSOEVER IS TO BE BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIEVED BY EVERY MAN IS TRUE.</p>
                  <p>But every wicked man is to believe that he ſhall be ſaved:</p>
                  <p>Therefore it is true, that every wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man ſhall be ſaved.</p>
                  <p>Here you muſt note, that every wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man is not to believe abſolutely, that he ſhall be ſaved, but conditionally, <hi>viz.</hi> If he repent, and believe in Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another Example.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AUREAM QUISQUIS MEDIOCRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATEM DILIGIT; tutus careat abſoleti Sordibus tecti, careat invidenda Sobrius aula.</hi> Horat.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41178:54"/>THE GOLDEN MEANE WHO IS CONTENT WITHALL, Wants no ſpacious Pallace, nor envied Hall.</p>
                  <p>By written Idea's you may conſerve all Characters, ſingle Letters, naked Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, calculations of Nativities, Coſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical Deſcriptions and Proofs, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all Words, Phraſes and Sentences, not to be aptly expreſſed otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>Now having diſpatched all written I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas, and ſuch as are ſingle, we will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the compound.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Compound Idea's.</head>
               <p>THis kind is compounded of ſingle I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's, repreſenting either a naked word or ſentence: A compound Idea ſignifying a ſingle word, conſiſteth of a Fictitious and written Idea; As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</p>
               <p>If you were to remember <hi>(Edline)</hi> a friends Name, imagine <hi>(Ed)</hi> written on the oppoſite Wall on the right hand, and a <hi>line</hi> extended thence all along to the left aſide.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:41178:55"/>
               <p> So <hi>Lambert</hi> may be retained by a Lamb placed in one of the Repoſitories, and <hi>[ert]</hi> written on the oppoſite Wall on the left hand.</p>
               <p>Many words may be conveniently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited by Idea's compounded of fictiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and written Idea's.</p>
               <p>A compound Idea repreſenting an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſentence, is twofold, conſiſting either of a Direct and Written Idea, or of a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Written Idea; the nature of both will appear perſpicuous by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Example of an Idea, compounded of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and written Idea.</head>
                  <p>In the third Book of <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Elegies, the Fable of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Danaes,</hi> is thus morally applyed.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jupiter</hi> admonitus nihil eſſe potentius auro,</l>
                     <l>Corruptae pretium Virginis ipſe fuit.</l>
                     <l>Dum merces aberat durus pater, ipſa ſevera,</l>
                     <l>Aerati poſtes, ferrea turris erat.</l>
                     <l>Sed poſtquam ſapiens in munere venit adulter</l>
                     <l>Prebuit ipſa ſinus, &amp; dare juſſa dedit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:41178:55"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jove</hi> having heard Gold was of greateſt power,</l>
                     <l>Would for a Maiden-head himſelf have ſold:</l>
                     <l>Without a Bribe, Father and Maid look't ſowre,</l>
                     <l>Braſs gates and Iron Walls did him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold;</l>
                     <l>Till in a ſhower of Gold wiſe <hi>Jove</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending,</l>
                     <l>The Daughter lov'd, the Father did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>To remember this Moral, imagine the ſtory of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Danaes,</hi> drawn to the life in the upper part of a large frame hanging againſt the oppoſite Wall, and theſe Verſes of <hi>Ovid</hi> writ according to the uſual manner, in the lower part, which is vacant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another Example.</head>
                  <p>The ſeven Electoral Princes firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted <hi>Otho,</hi> third Emperor of that Name, and Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the fift, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by <hi>Manlius,</hi> in theſe Verſes.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:41178:56"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Moguntinenſis, Trevirenſis, Colonenſis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Atque Palatinus Dapifer, Dux portitur enſis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Marchio Prepoſitus camere, Pincerna Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Prelates of <hi>Mentz, Trevers</hi> and <hi>Colen.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Palſgrave</hi> Carver,<note n="a" place="margin">Of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg.</note> Marquiſs Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain,</l>
                     <l>The<note n="b" place="margin">Of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria.</note> Duke Sword-bearer, Cup-bearer the<note n="c" place="margin">Of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia.</note> King.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Suppoſe an Emperor ſitting on a throne in one of the Repoſitories, ſeven Princes ſtanding about him, and theſe Verſes writ on a table, hanging againſt the oppoſite Wall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another Example.</head>
                  <p>An Epigram of Sir <hi>Hugh,</hi> a vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Knight, taken out of <hi>Nicholas Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sepelapis motus non fit muſcoſus, ut aiunt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At barbam é bello retulit</hi> Hugo <hi>domum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Moſs (as they ſay) grows on no rowling ſtone;</l>
                     <l>Yet Sir <hi>Hugh</hi> from the Wars brought a Beard home.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:41178:56"/>
                  <p> Imagine an armed Knight, of a fierce Martial aſpect, with a long Beard, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a memorial place, bearing a white Shield on his left arm, wherein this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram is inſcribed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>An Epitaph upon the Empreſs <hi>Matil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>England;</hi> Wife of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror; and Mother of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Magna ortu, majorque viro, ſed maxima prole;</l>
                     <l>Hic jacet <hi>Henrici</hi> filia, ſponſa parens.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By Birth Great, Wedlock greater, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in Progeny,</l>
                     <l>Here lies the Daughter, Spouſe, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Henry.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Fancy this Epitaph graven on the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of an Alablaſter tomb, ſtanding in a memorial place.</p>
                  <p>All Hiſtories, Acts, Fables, Apologies, Morals deſcribed in Verſe, or other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; alſo Epigrams, Epitaphs, Anagrams and Mottoes may be retained in Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41178:57"/>by an Idea compounded of a Direct and Written.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Example of an Idea compounded of a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative and Written.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theodore Beza</hi> writeth thus, under the Emblem of a man ſpitting towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Cernis, ut hic foedo coelum qui conſpuit ore,</l>
                     <l>Non coelum, imo ſuos conſpuit ore ſinus:</l>
                     <l>Et tu coelorum Dominum contemptor, in illum</l>
                     <l>Non quot verba jacis, tot tibi probra vomis?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This Drivil who doth ſpit at Heaven high;</l>
                     <l>Not Heaven, but his boſom doth defile;</l>
                     <l>So contemners of Divine Majeſty</l>
                     <l>Do hurt themſelves, not God, by ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vile.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>In the upper part of a table hanging againſt the oppoſite Wall, imagine the picture of a man with his hands on his ſides, his legs ſtradling, and his head ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded backward towards Heaven, ſpitting thereat; this <hi>Tetraſtichon</hi> written under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, according to the uſual manner in Emblems.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:41178:57"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Theodore Beza</hi> hath another Embleme of a Circumference, equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant on every ſide from its Center, with theſe Verſes.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Cernis ut haec medium cingat teres undique punctum</l>
                     <l>Linea, &amp; hinc spacio diſtet &amp; inde pari.</l>
                     <l>Scilicet illa refert, quod nos tegit undique coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</l>
                     <l>Tellurem hoc punctum quod tenet ima no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat,</l>
                     <l>Cur igitur doleas? quorſum (dic quaeſo) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores</l>
                     <l>Tu, patria pepulit quem pietatis amor?</l>
                     <l>Coelum ſi verſus tendis, quocunque recedes,</l>
                     <l>Hinc ſpacio coelum cernis &amp; inde pari.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>See how this Circumference doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe</l>
                     <l>The middle point, like diſtant every where:</l>
                     <l>The Circle, Heaven round about us ſhows,</l>
                     <l>The Center noteth Earth which doth us bear.</l>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:41178:58"/>
                     <l>Why then (I pray) thy labour blam'ſt thou ſo,</l>
                     <l>Who art expel'd thy countrey for Gods love?</l>
                     <l>If thou to Heaven tend, where e're thou go,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſeeſt all places like near Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>In the upper part of a fair large table, fancy a center and circumference to be deſcribed, with theſe Verſes writ under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Magnus Ariſtoteles trutinando cacumina re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</l>
                     <l>In duo diviſit quicquid in orbe fuit.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Great <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> weighing all things here,</l>
                     <l>Concluded, in the World but two there were.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Suppoſe two Parallel circles drawn in the upper part of a table, in the center of which, let the figure 2. be written, and underneath this Diſtich, whereby is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified Subjects and Accidents.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:41178:58"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,<bibl>
                           <hi>Heſiod.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Lord hath pleaſed openly to place</l>
                     <l>The ſweat of Virtue before each man's face.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Suppoſe the verſicle of <hi>Heſiod</hi> elegant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly painted at the foot of <hi>Cebes</hi> table.</p>
                  <p>All Emblems, Hyeroglyphical Sentences or illuſtrated with ſimilyes, may be depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited in Repoſitories by a Relative and written Idea; of which the Picture occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying the upper part of the Table, is a a Relative Idea, and that written under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, a Scriptile. So much for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Idea's, and all the other kinds.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of chuſing Ideas.</head>
               <p>IT is ſufficiently manifeſt out of the five precedent chapters, what <hi>Idea,</hi> and how qualified, every thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred doth appropriate to it ſelf; but to render all more perſpicuous in this chapter, I will briefly ennumerate the Rules diſperſed in ſeveral places, for
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41178:59"/>choice of Idea's; though ſuch Recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation may be accounted tautology; yet it is very profitable; the Rules follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 1. All Hiſtories, Actions, Fables, Apologies, common buſineſſes, viſible things, or conceived under a viſible form, all ſentences whoſe ſubject or matter is viſible, and without any dependent writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten illuſtration, ought to be laid up in the Repoſitories by a Direct Idea, in quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty equal, augmented or contracted. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 2. All Hiſtories, Actions, Fables, Apologies, Morals and Similyes, remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for ſome coherent Verſes or Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as all Epigrams, Epitaphs, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams and Impreſſes are generally to be expreſſed by a compound Idea, conſiſting of a Direct and Scriptile. <hi>Cap</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 3. All Emblems and Sentences il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated by ſome notable Example, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Hyeroglyphically, are to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in Repoſitories by a compound Idea, conſiſting of a Relative and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 4. All Characters, ſingle Letters, nakes Numbers, Calculations of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities, Coſmographical deſcriptions and citations, are to be always diſpoſed in Repoſitories by a Scriptile Idea.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:41178:59"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 5. All ſingle words ſignifying no viſible thing, whoſe Idea either relative, fictitious, or compound of fictitious and ſcriptile, doth preſently occur, is to be ſo placed in the Repoſitory, either relative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fictitiouſly, or compoundly: If no ſuch Idea occurr, then it is to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by a Scriptile Idea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 6. All Phraſes and Sentences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible by a Direct Idea, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by a Relative Idea, or compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a Relative and Scriptile, if any preſent it ſelf commodiouſly, or if no ſuch offer it ſelf quickly, by a Scriptile Idea. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.10. &amp; 11.</p>
               <p>So much ſhall ſuffice for choice of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The manner of Repoſing Ideas.</head>
               <p>NOw there remains to ſpeak of the manner of laying up Idea's in their places, to which purpoſe take theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Rules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 1. Every Idea is to be placed in its order, <hi>viz.</hi> that which firſt occurreth
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41178:60"/>in the firſt place; the ſecond in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place of the firſt Repoſitory; the the third in the firſt, the fourth in the ſecond place of the ſecond Repoſitory; fift in the firſt, the ſixt in the ſecond place of the third Repoſitory; the like method is to be uſed in all the Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, till all the Idea's be placed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 2. Due quantity, convenient ſite, colour of the Repoſitory, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar attributes, are to be impoſed on each Idea, and very carefully minded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 3. After you have rightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the firſt Idea of any Repoſitory, note it very diligently with the eye of your mind, as if it really ſtood there, obſerving its kind, ſubject, quantity, ſite, attribution of the Repoſitories co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and other ſuch like peculiar attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, if it have any. For example, whether the Idea depoſited in the firſt place of any Repoſitory (as to the kind) be direct; as to the ſubject, concerning a man; in reſpect of quantity, equal; in regard of ſight, placed on the ground; and as to peculiar attributes, whether moving or yeilding a ſound; go over all theſe things in your mind, ſaying, The Idea which I have here beſtowed, is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41178:60"/>of a man, equal, placed on the ground, moving and yeilding a ſound: For by ſuch conſiderations an Idea is more firmly graven in memory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 4. After you have fitly diſpoſed the ſecond Idea of any Repoſitory, you muſt excogitate fome apt relation thereof to the former, in reſpect of like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or unlikeneſs of ſite, likeneſs or unlikeneſs of ſubject; or elſe in regard of the action of the latter Idea refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the former; you can pitch upon no Idea which may not be related to the former by one of theſe five wayes, which ſhall plainly appear by example: if both <hi>Idea's</hi> of one Repoſitory, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent and ſubſequent, be fixed to the wall, placed on a table, the ground, or under ground, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they agree in ſite: But if one be faſtened to the Wall, the other placed on a Table, on the ground or under ground, they are unlike in ſite: When the ſubject of both <hi>Idea's</hi> is Juſtice, Sin, a Man, War or Sleep, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they agree in ſubject; but when the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of one <hi>Idea</hi> is Juſtice, of the other Drunkenneſs, the one of a man, the other of a ſtone, or any other oppoſite thing, they diſagree in ſubject. Taken an
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41178:61"/>example of transferring the action of a latter Idea to a former: Suppoſe that a man in a Gown, ſitting at a Table, and over-looking ſome Books of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, with Counters lying ready to compute the total ſum, be an Idea diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the firſt place of a Repoſitory; and the Idea to be placed in the ſecond room of the Repoſitory, be a Farryer giving a Horſe a Drench with a Horn: In this caſe, that the action of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may have ſome dependance on the former, imagine that the Horſe (as ſoon as the drench is poured into his mouth) leaps back and diſturbeth the man in his reckoning, who ſits at the Table in the firſt place of the Repoſitory. This mutual Relation of Idea's placed in the ſame Repoſitory, is as it were a linking of them together, and doth admirably conduce to the remembrance of both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 5. If two or more diſtinct Idea's concur, whoſe relation to one another is found ſo near, as if they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined together; beſtow them in one ſame Memorial Place: As if the Idea immediately preceding be a Silver Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon full of fragrant Water, ſet upon a joyned Stool, and the ſubſequent Idea
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:41178:61"/>be an idle man doing nothing; you may conjoin theſe two Idea's in one, imagining that this man waſheth his hands in that odoriferous Water; ſo if the former Idea be two Virgins talking together, the latter a Skein of Green Silk, to join theſe two Ideas by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per connexion, you may fancy that one of the Virgins holdeth the Skein upon her wriſts, whileſt the other windeth it off her hands into a bottom. In like manner if the Antecedent Idea be Scriptile, and the Conſequent likewiſe Scriptile, if ſo be you allow ſpace e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the Table, the latter may be ſubſcribed under the former in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient diſtance from one another. Thus three Scriptile Ideas concurring together, if they be not too large for one Table, may be ſuppoſed written therein; the firſt in the higheſt place, the ſecond in the middle, the third in the loweſt, allowing nevertheleſs a fit diſtance. But alwayes when you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize two or three Ideas in one place, you muſt remember carefully, that ſo many Ideas were conſtituted in ſuch a place.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:41178:62"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 6. When you have laid up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Idea</hi> in its <hi>Place,</hi> (whether it be in the firſt or ſecond <hi>Room</hi> of the <hi>Repoſitory</hi>) peruſe all the foregoing <hi>Idea's</hi> in their order, if you have time, that they may reſide more deeply in <hi>Memory,</hi> and make the ſtronger impreſſion in minde. <hi>For as a School-boy by often reading over his leſſon, learneth it by heart,</hi> ſo the more frequently you peruſe <hi>Idea's,</hi> the more firmly you will retain them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 7. Laſtly, have a care not to load your <hi>Memory</hi> with a more nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous multitude of <hi>Idea's</hi> then is fit, for as it is unwholſome to burthen the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach above its ſtrength, ſo alſo to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelm the <hi>Memory</hi> with multiplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Idea's,</hi> doth lead into great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fufuſion. Temperate men admit only ſo much meat as they think they can well concoct; ſo do you only commit ſuch worthy things to <hi>Memory,</hi> as you truſt faithfully to remember; for it is better firmly to retain a few remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, then many of mean baſe nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:41178:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> Of the practiſe of the Art of Memory.</head>
               <p>I Think now convenient to illuſtrate the premiſed precepts by examples, whereby the practiſe of this Art, may be rendred more facile. Firſt, I will propoſe examples of common affairs, afterward of obſervations; Laſtly, I will briefly exhibit the Art of <hi>Dictating,</hi> and <hi>diſcharging</hi> of <hi>Memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Examples of ordinary buſineſs.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. Suppoſe (as taking it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you were to go to ſome great Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Town, it concerns not our purpoſe whether the place be known, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, and intend in the firſt place to enquire the price of <hi>Seed Barlie:</hi> i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine then in the firſt <hi>Place</hi> of the firſt <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> (that is the part on the right hand) you ſee a man meaſuring <hi>Barlie</hi> out of a Sack into a Buſhel, with a company of men ſtanding about him,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41178:63"/>as is the uſual manner in <hi>Markets,</hi> not forgetting to fancy the <hi>Buſhell</hi> handles to be <hi>Gold,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Idea</hi> in ſome part may be related to the <hi>Repoſitory</hi> in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, as is required in the ſixth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Moreover, That in the ſame Town liveth a <hi>Labourer</hi> whom you know, and muſt enquire out to work in your <hi>Hay-harveſt;</hi> fancy him to ſtand in the ſecond place (on the left hand) of the firſt <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> ſharpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Golden Sythe</hi> on a <hi>whetſtone,</hi> as it were preparing for ſuch Ruſtical im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment: I ſay <hi>Golden Sythe,</hi> that it may participate of the colour of the <hi>Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;</hi> this <hi>Idea</hi> agreeth with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in ſight and ſubject, for both <hi>Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a's</hi> of this <hi>Repoſitory</hi> are of men, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on the ground.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. Furthermore, That in your Journey, our minde full of Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is transferred from ordinary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, to <hi>Philoſophical</hi> Contemplation, and in ſuch Meditation you pitch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſomething worthy further diſcuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; place the <hi>Idea</hi> thereof in the firſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:41178:63"/>
                     <hi>Room</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if this were your Meditation; <hi>Even as Terreſtrial exhalations condenſed are the materiall cauſe of the Thunder-ſtone, though engendered in the aire, which is no Matrix of ponderous bodies: So of the rayes (which are as it were exhalations) of cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial bodies, there is generated a certain ſubſtance, called</hi> Quinteſſence, <hi>which by commixion with the four Elements, through their tenacity, groweth into one with them, whereby they are altered, and indewed with new forms, according to the diſpoſition of the matter into which thoſe celeſtial rayes are conveyed, the hand of the Almighty di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them.</hi> This <hi>Idea</hi> muſt be aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, Chapter 3. Imagine therefore a multitude of <hi>Thunder-ſtones,</hi> heaped up in the midſt of the firſt <hi>Memorial place,</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> ſome of the uppermoſt guilded with <hi>Silver,</hi> to repreſent the colour of the <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. A while after you call to minde ſome <hi>Aromatical Spices</hi> you are to buy: To remember which, fancy the ſecond place of the ſecond <hi>Repoſitorie</hi> convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a <hi>Grocers ſhop,</hi> the oppoſite
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41178:64"/>wall garniſhed with Neſts of Boxes full of ſeveral Spices, with Titles writ up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Boxes, after the uſual mode; two foot on this ſide the wall, let there ſtand a Counter, the Wares expoſed thereon you are to buy: as if the firſt thing you nominate to buy be <hi>Pepper,</hi> let a <hi>Silver</hi> Box full of <hi>Pepper</hi> ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the further end of the Counter; if the ſecond thing deſigned be <hi>Nutmegs,</hi> place a looſe bagge of <hi>Silver gilt Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs</hi> in the middle of the Counter; if the third be <hi>Sugar,</hi> ſet a <hi>Sugar loafe</hi> on the hither end of the Counter, with a <hi>Silver</hi> ſtring tyed about the top, that it may in ſome part bear the colour of the <hi>Repoſitarie.</hi> In this caſe you muſt remember that three <hi>Idea's</hi> were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed in one <hi>Place,</hi> whoſe coherence with the <hi>Idea</hi> in the other <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> is taken from their unlikeneſſe of ſight; for that <hi>Idea</hi> was heaped on the ground, theſe three are placed upon a Counter.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. Your next incident buſineſſe is to remember to ſpeak with a <hi>Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> of the ſame town (a man of a very great repute and credit for knowledge
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41178:64"/>in the Law) about a friends ſute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending in <hi>Chancery:</hi> Imagine that <hi>Counſellour</hi> in a Lawyers Gown, ſitting in a Chair, overlooking ſome writings, in the firſt <hi>Place</hi> of the third <hi>Repoſitory;</hi> ſeeing his Gown is black, you need no other attribution of colour of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">VI. If another new occaſion preſent it ſelf to minde, as that you are to buy a piece of <hi>Black Velvit</hi> of a <hi>Mercer</hi> in that town; the ſecond <hi>Place</hi> of the third <hi>Repoſitory</hi> muſt be transform'd into a <hi>Mercers</hi> ſhop, a piece of <hi>Black Velvet</hi> neatly laid in folds of equal length, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Counter, which doth in like manner as well denote the <hi>Repoſitories</hi> colour, as the Gown of the <hi>Counſellour</hi> ſitting in the former <hi>Place;</hi> whence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is deduced a manifeſt relation to the precedent <hi>Idea,</hi> the Lawyers Gown ſuppoſed to be lined with <hi>Velvet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="examples">
                  <head>Examples of remarkable Obſervations.</head>
                  <p>If you dined the ſame day among many learned men at an <hi>Ordinary,</hi> and in their diſcourſe did obſerve ſome
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41178:65"/>things worthy of further conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the <hi>Idea's</hi> of ſuch Obſervations, are to be repoſited in their following <hi>Repoſitories,</hi> in the ſame order as they occur.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. The firſt Remarkable ſentence may be this, <hi>Deſire of things not attaina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, procureth wretched madneſſe. I</hi> would ſignifie this Sentence relatively, in the firſt <hi>Place</hi> of the fourth <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> by ſome young man aparelled in <hi>Blew ſilk, deeply enamoured</hi> of a Virgine nobly deſcended, whoſe enjoyment he could not expect, weeping and lying on the ground, till ſurpriſed with <hi>Melancholy,</hi> he became mad: the truth of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is evidently demonſtrated by this Example.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The ſecond <hi>Sentence</hi> may be that of the Poet <hi>Lucretius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Praeterea ſi nulla fuit generalis origo</l>
                     <l>Terrarum &amp; Coeli, ſemperque aeterna fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere.</l>
                     <l>Cur ſupra bellum <hi>Thebanum,</hi> &amp; funera <hi>Trojae,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Non alias alii quoque res cecinere Poetae?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:41178:65"/>
                     <l>Beſides if God did not Heaven create, And Earth, they are Eternal, and each thing:</l>
                     <l>Beyond the <hi>Theban</hi> War, and <hi>Troys</hi> ſad fate,</l>
                     <l>Why do not Poets then, elder deeds ſing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>The <hi>Idea</hi> of this <hi>Sentence</hi> is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of a <hi>Direct</hi> and <hi>Scriptile,</hi> you muſt imagine the Wars of <hi>Thebes</hi> and <hi>Troy</hi> ſeverally depainted in the upper part of a large ſpacious Table, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath theſe Verſes of <hi>Lucretia's</hi> fairly written; becauſe it is put in the fourth <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> ſuppoſe a <hi>Blew Line</hi> three in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches broad, drawn between the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of <hi>Thebes</hi> and <hi>Troy</hi> beſieged: The <hi>Line</hi> is more remarkable in this <hi>Idea,</hi> ſhewing the Pictures to be devided into two equal parts, Chapter 6. The <hi>frame</hi> muſt hang againſt rhe oppoſite wall of the ſecond place of the fourth <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> this <hi>Idea</hi> may be referred to the <hi>Idea</hi> in the former <hi>Room</hi> from their diverſe ſituations, the precedent placed on the ground, this hanging againſt the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite wall.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:41178:66"/> 
                     <hi>III.</hi> Let this be the third <hi>Sentence, Every thing that is juſt, is not agreeable to equity,</hi> Manlius Torquatus, <hi>did juſtly, but not equally, when he commanded his ſon, a couragious young man (who had deſerved well of the Republick) to be beheaded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that contrary to his order, provoked by the enemy, he brought forth the Roman Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and joyned battel in his father the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals abſence, though he was Victor.</hi> The <hi>Idea</hi> of this <hi>Sentence</hi> is <hi>Direct,</hi> to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the firſt <hi>Place</hi> of the fifth <hi>Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> imagine a Martial man ſtanding there in compleat armour; a plume of Feathers in his Creſt, of a ſevere frown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſpect, a great Golden chain (the <hi>Index</hi> of his name) girt round about his body, holding a <hi>Red Trunchion</hi> in his right hand, applyed to his ſides; and ſeeming imperiouſly to command one clothed like an Executioner, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Ax ſprinkled with blood, to put his Sonne, arrayed in <hi>Red ſilk,</hi> to death.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>IV. A man may wittingly do his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour a prejudice, without committing an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; for if there be two Innes in one Town, the one Inkeeper muſt needs endamage the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41178:66"/>by endeavouring to draw Gueſts to his own Inne, yet is ſuch damage without injury, nor condemned by any Law.</hi> This <hi>Idea</hi> is <hi>Direct,</hi> but in quantity contracted. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine therefore in the ſecond <hi>Place</hi> of the fifth <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> a Town elegant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed on a Table, hanging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the oppoſite Wall, containing two Innes, the ſigns of both ſuſtained by Poſts of a <hi>Red colour;</hi> it hath reference to the former <hi>Idea</hi> in reſpect of ſubect, for Juſtice is the baſis of both <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">V. <hi>No excellent wit it free from ſome mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> may be expreſſed Relatively by a learned man who through too great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of minde in ſtudy, is become frantick, wearing a <hi>yellow</hi> Plume of Feathers in his hat (yellow being the colour of the ſixth <hi>Repoſitory</hi>) and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying ſome childiſh <hi>Geugaws</hi> in his hands, at which he laughs ſo heartily, that the <hi>Reponant</hi> heareth him; he is to be ſet in the firſt <hi>Place</hi> of the ſixth <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory,</hi> near the oppoſite wall.</p>
                  <p>Ilia <hi>a veſtal Virgine, great with childe by Mars, brought forth two twinns,</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus <hi>and</hi> Remus <hi>at one birth , which ſhee put forth to be nurſed by a notable harlot, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:41178:67"/>Lupa,</hi> of whom all Bawdy-Houſes after in <hi>Latine</hi> were called <hi>Lupanaria:</hi> Hence certainly aroſe the Fable, that they were nouriſhed by a She-Wolf: <hi>Romus</hi> in proceſs of time being created King, impoſed his own Name upon <hi>Rome,</hi> by the Citizens whereof in flattery, he was called <hi>Romulus.</hi> This is a Direct Idea; imagine in the ſecond place of the ſixth Repoſitory, a She-Wolf ſuckling two Twins with her dandling Dugs, as if they were her own Whelps, her neck inviron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a yellow Collar, which with howling doth divert the mad man in the precedent place from his mirth. This Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is in regard of action, paſſing from the latter Idea to the former, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fifth Rule of the 13. Chap. Moreover both Idea's of this Repoſitory agree in clamorous ſound, and in their ſite on the ground.</p>
                  <p>Milo <hi>of</hi> Croton, <hi>a famous Wreſtler, firſt crowned in the</hi> Olympick <hi>Games, when through age he had left off his youthful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, and travelled through ſome Woodlands of</hi> Italy, <hi>eſpyed an Oak near the way rifted in the middle, and willing (as is ſuppoſed) to try whether any of his ancient vigour remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thruſt his hands into the Clefts of the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41178:67"/>Tree) to rend down the middle part; but the Oak thus forcibly writhed (ſo ſoon as his violence ceaſed) returned to its priſtine E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and cloſing faſt upon his hands, detein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a prey for wild Beaſts,</hi> Aul. Gell. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. Noc. 15 16. The Idea of this Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is Direct, of equal magnitude to be placed in the firſt place of the ſeventh Repoſitory, in the midſt whereof I fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy a cleft Oak full of Green Leaves and Acorns, in that cleft of which a ſtrong great limbed man, crowned with Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, is faſt held by the hands, who ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding back his head and body, cryeth with a horrible vociferation, that you really ſeem not onely to ſee his wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed body, and the Beaſts preying about him; but alſo hear his outcries and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>VIII. To drive forward the night with old Wives fables.</hi> This phraſe is expreſſed by a Direct Idea, ſuppoſing the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Wall of the ſecond place in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Repoſitory, converted into the form of a Chimney, containing a great Fire, about which ſome women ſit goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipping, among them an old woman in a Green Gown (like an Ape in Purple) laughing and holding up her hands,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41178:68"/>her countenance, geſture and action conformable, tells a Tale to the reſt, which affecteth the whole Conventicle of Women with mirth. The relation of this Idea to the former, ariſeth from the great noiſe in both, onely the former is a lamentable doleful ſound, this a merry jocund noiſe.</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. <hi>Men are certainly more ancient then the Heatheniſh Gods, becauſe theſe are the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers invention.</hi> The Idea of this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is direct, <hi>viz.</hi> a Statuary in a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Waſtcoat, faſhioning an image, which is to be diſpoſed in the firſt place of the eighth Repoſitory.</p>
                  <p n="10">X. Every particle of Snow, if it be not ſomewhat melted, is of a ſix angu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar figure, proclaiming the admirable Artifice of the Creator, to ſuch as curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly contemplate the ſame. The <hi>Idea</hi> of this Sentence is Direct, in quantity augmented; for ſeeing one flake of Snow is ſo ſmall, that beſtowed in a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial place, it cannot be ſeen afar off; a heap of Snow is to be ſubſtituted in the middle of the ſtage of the ſecond place of the eighth Repoſitory; and becauſe this <hi>Idea</hi> hath nothing of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in it (the proper colour of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory)
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41178:68"/>fancy a Purple Streamer two foot high, placed in the midſt of the heap of Snow, Cap. 6. The Relation may be deduced from the ſubject, there being Artifice in both <hi>Ideas,</hi> though of much greater excellency and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the latter, then the former, Snow being a Divine Artifice, a Statue but humane.</p>
                  <p n="11">XI. <hi>There are three moſt beautiful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of three very deformed Daughters;</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity <hi>breedeth</hi> Contempt, Truth <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth</hi> Hatred, <hi>and</hi> Peace <hi>engendereth</hi> idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This <hi>Idea</hi> is Direct, imagining in the firſt place of the ninth Repoſitory, three moſt amiable women in very rich Apparel, having Garlands on their heads, ſitting upon three-legged Stools, and giving ſuck to three crying miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Children, lapped up in pure white ſwadling Clothes: The cry of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren gives this <hi>Idea</hi> a loud ſound.</p>
                  <p n="12">XII. <hi>A</hi> Priviledge <hi>is that which is granted in favour of certain perſons contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to common right, and is called</hi> Privilege quaſi privata lege, <hi>that is, by a private law.</hi> This may be expreſſed relatively, by ſome well known perſon deeply in debt, who procured a <hi>Priviledge</hi> for
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:41178:69"/>himſelf fairly written in white Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, authorized with the Great Seal, to protect himſelf from moleſtation of Creditors: The Parchment of the ſame colour with the Repoſitory, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all other aſſignation of colour as uſeleſs. Laſtly, A dependency upon the former <hi>Idea,</hi> may be deduced from a tranſient action, ſuppoſing that this man in the ſecond place, looking on the Women in the firſt place, doth ſalute them very curteouſly and civilly after the gentile poſture, by whom he is mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſaluted again.</p>
                  <p n="13">XIII. <hi>He doth not live, who takes no care but to live.</hi> The <hi>Idea</hi> of this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is Scriptile, and muſt be ſuppoſed written in a large white Table, noting ſuch obſervations as you had formerly delivered to this purpoſe, which may be ſuppoſed committed to the man ſtanding in the ſecond place of the laſt Repoſitory to hold, as having no other employment, whereby he is ſomewhat diverted from conference with the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; by this means both theſe latter <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's</hi> are as it were one, Cap. 13. Rul. 5. and being depoſited in the ninth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory, needeth no attribution of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41178:69"/>as is ſhewn before, Cap. 10. Rul. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">XIV. The ancient <hi>Gauls</hi> and <hi>Britains</hi> uſed <hi>Engliſh Maſtives</hi> in Military ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, inſtead of Souldiers. <hi>Strabo.</hi> This Idea is direct, but contracted by reaſon of the great ſpace, to be aſſigned for a field Battel: Let therefore this skirmiſh of men and dogs be imagined inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven artificially in colours to the life. in the hangings of the oppoſite Wall of the firſt place of the tenth Repoſitory, the Collars of the Maſtives of Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon colour (the proper colour of the tenth Repoſitory, full of iron ſpikes.</p>
                  <p n="15">XV <hi>Good works juſtifie faith, faith ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth the perſon,</hi> is a Scriptile <hi>Idea;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſuppoſe this ſentence fairly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (according to the Rules in the tenth Chapter) in a large ſquare table, the frame of Cinnamon colour, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the oppoſite Wall of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place. The relation of one <hi>Idea</hi> to the other, is taken from their like ſite both hanging againſt the Wall.</p>
                  <p n="16">XVI. <hi>Dic ubi tunc eſſet, cum praeter, cum nihil eſſet?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tunc ubi nunc, in ſe, quoniam ſibi ſufficit ipſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:41178:70"/>
                     <l>Say where was God, when him beſide Not any thing had been?</l>
                     <l>Then there where now, in himſelf, for Himſelf ſufficeth him.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>This is likewiſe a <hi>Scriptile Idea,</hi> and may be fitly comprehended in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the preceding <hi>Idea,</hi> obſerving ſuch Rules as are delivered concerning repoſiting a <hi>Scriptile Idea,</hi> and noting that two Idea's are comprized in this place, <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Rule</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. In the year 1530. in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, Emperor, the <hi>Germane</hi> Princes exhibited their Confeſſion of Faith at <hi>Augspurgh,</hi> with a ſolemn pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation becauſe of that perillous time, whence afterward they, and all ſuch as embraced the ſame confeſſion, were called <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> This Idea is Direct; but all the ten Repoſitories being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready occupied, you muſt imagine ten other Repositories of the ſame colour as the former, to be uſed in the ſame order as was propoſed in the 16. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: So the colour of the eleventh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory will be gold. I ſuppoſe in the firſt place thereof an Emperial Throne,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41178:70"/>adorned with badges of the Empire, glittering with Gold and Gems, upon which the Emperor crowned with a Golden Diadem ſitteth, to whom his Nobles bare-headed, preſent their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion fairly engroſſed in paper.</p>
                  <p n="18">XVIII. Philip <hi>King of</hi> Macedon, <hi>ſent a Prolix Epiſtle to the</hi> Laconians, <hi>wherein he did require ſome things which did not pleaſe them: They returned him an anſwer containing but one ſyllable</hi> (that is) Not, <hi>which the Writer did deſcribe in ſo great a Character, that it equalized a large Epiſtle. Another time the ſame</hi> Philip <hi>menaced the ſame people, That if he did once invade their Countrey, he would cauſe an utter extirpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them; the</hi> Laconians <hi>on the contrary ſent no other reply but this particle,</hi> ei, <hi>that is,</hi> if; <hi>inſinuating thereby, that the word</hi> if <hi>was well inſerted by</hi> Philip, <hi>who could never hope to penetrate their Region: Hence was derived the Proverb,</hi> Laconical brevity, This is a Direct Idea, theſe two words fancied to be drawn in two ſheets of paper, with a Golden Margent round about, an inch broad, and paſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an oppoſite Wall. Coherence with the former Idea offereth it ſelfe from ſimilitude of ſubject, ſuppoſing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41178:71"/>that theſe two words <hi>[not, if]</hi> contain an anſwer to the aforeſaid Confeſſion preſented to the Emperor.</p>
                  <p n="19">XIX. <hi>Paſſionate anger is temporary mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> This ſentence may be relatively exemplified in <hi>Saul,</hi> who tranſported with anger, endeavoured to ſmite <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> his moſt beloved Son and Heir, with a Javelin; imagining the point of the Javelin to be ſilver, that it may in ſomething repreſent the colour of the twelfth Repoſitory.</p>
                  <p>It will be unneceſſary now to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further, becauſe I think the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent examples will ſufficiently declare by what kind of Idea's all memorable things are to be expreſſed, and in what place to be depoſited. If you pleaſe to eſſay the rehearſal of all the Idea's of this Chapter in their order, without looking in the Book, provided you have firſt read them over with good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I doubt not but you will ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly confeſs the great utility and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of this act.</p>
                  <p>Any man may eaſily apprehend, though he were never admoniſhed, that obſervable notes of Sermons are to be laid up after the ſame manner, as theſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:41178:71"/>obſervations, which I have ſet down for better obſervation, as taken at a Banquet.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of Dictation and Repoſition.</head>
               <p>MOreover, the practical part of this Art is perſpicuouſly ſeen in the Exerciſes of <hi>Dictating</hi> and <hi>Repetition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The uſe of <hi>Dictating</hi> is, when a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is to dictate to ſeveral Scribes or Secretaries, what every one muſt write, ſo as to direct and exerciſe them all at once, which is frequently incumbent upon Princes and Generals of Armies in perillous times: In ſuch caſes there muſt be aſſigned a peculiar Repoſitory to every Scribe, wherein the affairs and ſentences by him to be diſpatched muſt be reported in order; that is, the firſt Repoſitory to the firſt Scribe, the ſecond Repoſitory to the ſecond, the third to the third, the fourth to the fourth, and ſo forth if there be more: All Idea's of things to be diſpatched by the firſt Secretary, muſt have ſome
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:41178:72"/>attribution of Gold appertaing to them; all Idea's of the ſecond Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, ſomething of Silver; of the third, ſomething of black, of the fourth, blew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this caſe alſo it is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to place two, three, or more Idea's if it be neceſſary, in one place of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory: All buſineſſes and ſentences being thus repoſited in order, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully digeſted before in mind, it is no difficult matter by the firſt Idea of the firſt Repoſitory, to dictate to the firſt Scribe what he muſt write firſt; by the firſt Idea of the ſecond Repoſitory, to tell the ſecond Scribe what he ſhall write; by the firſt Idea of the third Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory, to inform the third; and in like manner all the reſt in their order. Again, by the ſecond Idea of each Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitory, the ſecond ſentence is facile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered to each Scribe: By the third, every Scribes third buſineſs; by the fourth Idea their fourth, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the reſidue. This is the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, which by ſome is called the Art of Dictating.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repetition</hi> is when a man repeateth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences ſpoken by ſeveral perſons, ſo as to return each perſons ſentence in order as
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41178:72"/>it was delivered; as if ſix, ſeven, or more friends ſitting together (to experience your happy memory) do every one in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſpeak ſome ſentence, to have them repeated again, after the ſame or a retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade manner, which way they pleaſe; diſpoſe the Idea's of your firſt friends ſentences in the firſt Repoſitory; of your ſecond friend in the ſecond Repoſitory; of your third friend in the third, and ſo forward in the reſt. All which being rightly diſpoſed, you may with little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſtore to every friend his ſaying, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame order as they were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or in a retrograde or inverted or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>I have not thought expedient to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate theſe with Examples, becauſe I think them ſufficiently explained by what hath been already ſaid; as alſo, that this Exerciſe of Dictating and Repeating have little or no uſe, but vain oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; though I have inſerted them here, it was not done as neceſſary, but becauſe the knowledge of them did not ſeem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous for ſuch as are learned of this Art.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:41178:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of irregular Repoſition.</head>
               <p>I Have thought good to annex a few words of irregular Repoſition, which is onely one Rule, that is, a real Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory may be ſometimes ſubſtituted inſtead of a feigned, which irregularity is admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon a double occaſion:</p>
               <p>Firſt, A thing it ſelf being at hand, may be fitly uſed inſtead of its proper I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea: As if a man ſitting in his Study, light on ſome Book whoſe ſheets are tranſplaced, which he intendeth when he goes forth of his Study, to ſend to a Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binder to be amended: That Book is to be caſt at the threſhold of the Study, that the ſight thereof may admoniſh him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, to get it bound: So alſo if Ink be wanting, an Ink-Glaſs or Bottle may be ſet by the Book.</p>
               <p>Secondly, When a man muſt exone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate one or more Idea's, as ſoon as he hath repoſited them; as when ſomething offers it ſelf to a mans mind, talking to a powerful or rich man, which he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41178:73"/>convenient to be communicated to him with the firſt opportunity, let him ſpeedily repoſite the Idea of that thing in the ſame houſe, field, plain, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he then is, in ſome certain place converſant before his eyes, that he may be always put in mind to propound the ſame when occaſion ſerves: As if he think to do ſome friendly office for a perſon ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, by preferring ſome buſineſs of his to the rich man; let him imagine that Friend always obvious in ſome determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate place in ſight, not ſuffering the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſlip out of view, till he have cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly performed his officious enterpriſe. Or if there intervene ſome thought of buying fewel, whereof the rich man hath great plenty, let him ſuppoſe a great quantity of Wood piled up in ſome place not diſtant out of ſight: This is all I have to ſay of <hi>irregular Repoſition.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:41178:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of depoſiting Idea's.</head>
               <p>HAving ſpoken copiouſly of repoſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Idea's, now I will conclude with Depoſiting them.</p>
               <p>Depoſition of Idea's is, when things charged upon Memory by Idea's, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called, and the mind exonerated of them, the Memorial Places after ſuch Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being left empty, and prepared to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive new Idea's. Now in this caſe, if it happen at any time that an Idea negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently repoſited, is loſt or forgotten, when it ſhould be depoſited, the recovery thereof muſt be endeavoured by theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing conſiderations.</p>
               <p>Firſt, This is always aſſuredly known, every loſt Idea did bear the colour of his Repository, either in whole or part; therefore the firſt thing to be inquired is, in what reſpect the colour of the Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory did agree with the Idea ſought; by this ſole conſideration, forgotten Idea's are oft diſcovered.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:41178:74"/>
               <p> The Idea being not diſcovered thus, make diligent indagation for its relation to the Idea placed in the ſame Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in regard of ſite, ſubject or action, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Rul.</hi> 4. One Idea of a Repoſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being known, doth eaſily call the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to mind, by mutual dependence whereby they were connexed together, unleſs there did precede very negligent Repoſition.</p>
               <p>If ſtill you are diſappointed, happily you may find it out by repetition of ſuch things as are eſpecially remarkable in laying up Idea's, of which I have ſpoken in the 13. Chapter. That is by enquiring whether the latent Idea's was</p>
               <list>
                  <head>In reſpect of kind</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Direct,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Relative,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fictitious,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Scriptile,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Compound,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Double, treble, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:41178:75"/>
                  <head>In reſpect of ſubject,</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of God,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of Chriſt,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of Angels,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of Men,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of Animals.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In reſpect of quantity,</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Equal,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Augmented,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Contracted,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In reſpect of ſite,</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Under ground,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Upon ground,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Upon a Table,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Upon a Shelf,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Againſt a wall.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In reſpect of attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Moving,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quiet,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Giving a ſound.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Yeilding a ſmel.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>An Idea is oft recovered by diſcuſſing theſe few queſtions in a mans thoughts.</p>
               <p>If it be certain the forgot Idea was Scriptile, but the inſcription is in oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the firſt inquiry muſt be, whether it were a ſingle word, proof, phraſe, or
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:41178:75"/>ſentence or one or more clauſes; a ſingle word, proof, or principal word of a ſentence, may be regained by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying each Letter of the Alphabet in the ſame manner as is preſcribed in the ſecond Rule of Poetical Revocation, in the ſecond Book, Cap. 3. till you have obtained the firſt Letter; the other Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may be found by tranſcendencies and gilded Vowels; the chief Word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained, the reſt come eaſily to mind.</p>
               <p>If you cannot yet diſcover the Idea, have recourſe to the third and fourth Rules of Poetical Revocation, 2. Book. 3 Chap, an Idea being revocable in the ſame manner.</p>
               <p>Finally, if it continue irreparable by all theſe ways, let it paſs, and be no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſollicitous in ſearch thereof: For as a Book careleſly laid up in a Study, is not many times to be found when it is ſought, though you remove ſeveral Volumes; yet afterward comes to hand beyond expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, when another Book is reached that ſtands by it: So it doth oft happen in this buſineſs, though an Idea negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently repoſited, cannot be found when it is ſought, yet at another time when a Notion repoſited in the cell of Memory
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41178:76"/>near it, is excited, that alſo of its own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord diſcovereth it ſelf.</p>
               <p>If a man do prudently follow theſe Rules of recovering latent Ideas, as with <hi>Ariadnes</hi> thred, he will doubtleſs wind himſelf out of the Labyrinth of blind Oblivion, and with admirable facility recall to mind forgotten ſentences, and vaniſhed <hi>Idea's.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:41178:76"/>
            <head>A TREATISE Of cheriſhing <hi>Natural Memory.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of ſuch as debilitate Memory.</head>
               <p>NAtural Memory is a faculty which every man hath naturally to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and retain note-worthy things; if Memory be diligent in its Function, endeavour muſt be uſed to conſerve it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced; if it be impaired, care muſt be taken to have it reſtored and erected: <hi>I</hi> will therefore firſt treat of the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41178:77"/>of Natural Memory indamnified, afterward of the reſtauration thereof impaired.</p>
               <p>Three things conduce to preſerve Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Memory in good Eſtate, <hi>viz.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of ſuch things as debilitate Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; uſe of ſuch things as corroborate the ſame, and a well inſtituted method of living, whereby the Memorative fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty may be moſt preſerved in vigor.</p>
               <div type="conditions">
                  <head>Things that debilitate Memory are theſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Unwholſome air that is infected with vapour of ſtanding-waters, Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Woods, Priſons, Dunghils, Common Sewers, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Aire ſhut up from penetration of Wind and Sun; for air not purified by Wind or Sun, engendereth a malign ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous quality, like ſtanding water in Ponds and Lakes; therefore when you walk abroad, leave the Windows of your Chamber and Study open.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Windie aire,</hi> that is, agitated with violent winds.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Aire</hi> that procureth rain.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:41178:77"/> 5. <hi>Moiſt aire,</hi> ſuch as diſcendeth a little before Sun ſet, and hovereth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the earth all night, and ſome part of the morning, eſpecially in Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time places. Go not forth before the riſing Sun hath purified the aire by his Rayes, nor after Sun ſetting, when cloudy darkenſſe of night invadeth the aire.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Aire</hi> infected with ſmoke of ſtrong ſented combuſtible things, as <hi>Sea coales, Weeds, Turfe, Dung</hi> and <hi>Char-coales,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be well kindled.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. <hi>Drinks, Broths,</hi> and <hi>Decoctions</hi> made of unwholſome waters, offend the <hi>Memory,</hi> of which kinde is the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Ponds, Marſhes,</hi> of <hi>Ice</hi> and <hi>Snow</hi> diſſolved, as alſo of <hi>Muddie, Salt, Bitter,</hi> and <hi>ill ſmelling water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rain water,</hi> eſpecially falling in time of Thunder, or Lightning (becauſe it is lighteſt) is chiefly commended for Domeſtical uſes; but ſerveth only for preſent occaſion, by reaſon of its ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy corruption: Fountain or Spring Water challengeth the next place, which devolveth from Mountains, through ſtony craggy clifts; to this ſucceedeth <hi>River water,</hi> when the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41178:78"/>of the River is deep and gravelly; <hi>Well-water</hi> is ranked laſt, if it ſmell of Mudd; the Well muſt be cleanſed and purged by caſting in <hi>Lyme,</hi> and the bottome afterward covered with great ſtore of <hi>Chalk,</hi> through which the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bubling, is defecated and rendred more Salubrious. To conclude, the clearer, lighter, further diſtant from any taſte or ſmell, colder in Summer, hotter in Winter water is, the more wholeſome it is.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>Food</hi> hurteth the <hi>Memory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. If it be crude, as raw fleſh, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiled water, immature fruits, green hearbs, chiefly if they beef cold quail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If it be Vaporous, that is, reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the head with groſſe Vapors, as <hi>thick drinks, ſtrong wine, Beans, Peaſe, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Onyon,</hi> &amp;c. but <hi>Onyons</hi> are more noxious then the reſt, becauſe they loſe not their <hi>Malignity</hi> by <hi>Decoction,</hi> even then procuring the head-ach, offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eyes by cauſing obſtructions in the Optick nerves, dulling the Senſes, and raiſing troubleſome dreams.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If it be very moiſt, and engender phlegme, as <hi>Milk, Chickens</hi> before they
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41178:78"/>are feathered, young <hi>Piggs</hi> &amp;c. eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally any food that hath a ſlimie taſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If it digeſt ſlowly, as <hi>Cheeſe, marrow, fat,</hi> principally of <hi>Fiſh, fleſh</hi> of <hi>Cranes</hi> and <hi>Herons,</hi> fruit included in ſhells, as Wall-nuts, Small-nuts, Cheſt-nuts, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Variety of diſhes, diverſity even of wholeſome meats is evil, of Sauces worſt of all, diſtracting the ſtomack by concocting food of ſeveral qualities.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſſe healthfull perſons may eat any meats, though they be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſomwhat hurtfull, when the appetite doth as it were long; For ſuch victuals as the appetite doth greedily covet, the ſtomack doth earneſtly embrace, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Concoct and Tranſmit to the lower parts, whence they offend leſſe; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is ſafer to eat ſuch meats at Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then at ſupper.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. All <hi>Repletion of Drink, or food</hi> is hurtfull, chiefly of Bread; too much <hi>Repletion dulleth wit,</hi> and is a great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the <hi>Memorative faculty. Plato</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſoul is diſeaſed in a full fed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> It is often ſeen by experience, that if a learned or wiſe man, accuſtomed to live ſparingly through poverty, be
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41178:79"/>exalted to ſome eminent degree of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or honour, and doth afterward indulge his appetite by eating and drinking immoderately, he becomes leſſe learned and wiſe: The reaſon is by acceſſe of groſs humours to the brain, the Notional Figures imprinted therein before, by degrees wear out and vaniſh, and new figures take no ſuch deep impreſſion, but are quickly eraſed through overmuch humidity of the brain. Fly therefore <hi>Drunkenneſſe</hi> and <hi>Gluttony,</hi> as the mortalleſt enemies of a good <hi>Memory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">V. <hi>Sleep</hi> offendeth <hi>Memory.</hi> If it be Firſt, overmuch. Secondly, if taken in a windy place, or under <hi>Lunar raies.</hi> Thirdly, in the day, moſt of all with ſhoes on, or being miry. Fourthly, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the back, for it preventeth expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Excrements, at mouth and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, their proper conveyances, and cauſeth their Conflux to the back, whence ariſeth Obſtructions. Fifthly, upon the belly, becauſe it endama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the eyes, being dangerouſly preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to ſuch as are moleſted with Rhumes in their eyes.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. <hi>Venus,</hi> 1. if it be immoderate.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:41178:79"/>2. upon a full ſtomack. 3. when the body is leſſe moiſt, as at New Moon, in time of hunger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 4. when ſleep doth not follow, for it is requiſite that the looſned members of the body, be refreſhed by enſuing ſleep. Perſons very young or very ancient, of a frigid conſtitution, and all ſuch as finde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience after the act, muſt wholly abſtain therefrom.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. Coldneſſe of the hinder part of the head, of the neck, ſtomack, belly and feet.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. Labour or exerciſe of body. 1. Exceeding moderation, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſteth ſtrength. 2. In windy or moiſt places. 3. On a full ſtomack, which repleniſheth the head with crude Vapors, &amp; augmenteth Choller.</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. Idleneſs.</p>
                  <p n="10">X. Perturbation of mind; as anxious care, fear, grief, too much baſhfulneſs, covetous hope, Jealouſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">XI. Filthy deſires, as avarice, envy, thirſt of revenge, luſt, love of harlots, and the ardent Paſſion, <hi>Love.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">XII. Raſh anſwers.</p>
                  <p n="13">XIII. Diſorderly reading of Books, imitating Children in trivial Schools.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:41178:80"/> XIV. Night ſtudy.</p>
                  <p n="15">XV. Wearing head-hair over long.</p>
                  <p n="16">XVI. Dipping or waſhing the head in cold water.</p>
                  <p n="17">XVII. Diſtraction of mind about ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verl ſtudies at one time, as if a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter be intent at his private ſtudy, when his Schollers attend and repeat their leſſons.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of things corroborating Memory.</head>
               <p>OF this kind are theſe that follow. 1. Wholſome Air, that is clear, light, ſweet, open, milde, ſpeedily growing warm with the riſing ſun, and cold with his ſetting.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sweet ſents, for they comfort the heart, brain and mind, in ſome ſort nouriſh the Spirits, and indue the brain with a tenacious quality, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is more apt to retain <hi>Idea's,</hi> This is experimentally proved in hony compoſed of the breath of flowers, mingled with morning dew, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of hony being gummy.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:41178:80"/> 3. Of meats.</p>
               <p>Firſt, All ſuch as ingender good nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, that is, which procreat pure bloud, full of Spirits; ſuch are Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, Partridges, Pheaſants, Weather, mutton, Goats fleſh, and like meats as adminiſter pure aliment to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Brains of Partridges, Sparrows, Hares, Conies and Hens, which being dryer then the brains of other creatures, are thought to profit <hi>Memory</hi> very much; if <hi>Wekerus</hi> may be credited, brains of Hens frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eaten, hath recovered diverſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Phrenſie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Theſe herbs uſed in ſauces, <hi>Bawm, Bugloſs, Watercreſſes,</hi> in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which there is extant a Proverb, <hi>Ede naſturtium,</hi> Savorie, Beets, Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royall, Hyſope, Tyme, Nigella, Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary flowers, Cardnus Benedictus, theſe are not onely beneficial to exacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the <hi>Memory,</hi> but do alſo exhilarate the minde, and eaten laſt at ſupper, procure pleaſant dreams.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Waſhing the feet once a moneth in water moderately heated, wherein <hi>Bawm, Cammomill, Bay leaves,</hi> and other
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41178:81"/>odoriferous hearbs have been boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Exerciſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If If it be moderate, thereby un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proficable excrements are expelled, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat augmented, the motions of the Spirits rendred free, the body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers vigour, and the ſoul made more apt to perform its functions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it recreate the Spirits and all parts of the body exerciſed, alſo the Breaſt and Lungs by vociferation, ſuch are ſhooting, bowling, hunting, haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, but ſtool-ball playing, is by <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> preferred before them all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such as is done upon an empty ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomack.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In delightfull places, not ſubject to wind.</p>
               <p>Exerciſe muſt be moderate at firſt, more vehement in the middle, more remiſs at lattet end: Moreover let pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration precede exerciſe, by evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the belly, bladder, &amp; noſtrils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and extenſion of the members; in like manner after exerciſe, there is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtretching of the members, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate friction of the body with warm linnen, and cohibition of the Spirits.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:41178:81"/>Finally, your apparel cloſe fitted, walk leiſurely abroad, if the winde breath a gentle gale, otherwiſe within doors. Such perſons as are of exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot and dry Complexions, muſt abſtain from laborious excerciſes, uſing ſuch as are moderate and provoke ſweat leſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of a preſcript order of life.</head>
               <p>NOw in the next place I will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome precepts or Rules of well ordered living, (chiefly regarding Students, for whoſe ſakes this work was undertaken) in ſuch ſort that the <hi>Memorative</hi> faculty may be benefitted. The Rules are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 1. <hi>Divine aſſiſtance</hi> is to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently and frequently implored in Prayer, to ſanctifie our ſouls with Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial grace; for as the milde influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Celeſtial bodys immediatly transfuſed into our corporeal, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute much to the good eſtate thereof: ſo Divine influences of grace, infuſed
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:41178:82"/>by God into our ſouls, recreate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them much more: And ſeeing divine irradiations are alwaies volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there is doubtleſs no Rule more powerful or efficacious to procure the Lords good will towards us, then pious ſupplications-made to God in Chriſt, as <hi>James</hi> teſtifieth in his Epiſtle, 5. Chap. <hi>ver.</hi> 16, 17. nor is it imprudently ſaid,</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cedunt aſtra Deo, precibus Deus ipſe ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</l>
                  <l>The Stars give place to God, he to his peoples prayers.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 2. Comb your head every day backward, to looſen excrements from the hair roots, let it be done faſting, ſo ſoon as you are ready in a morning. Combing the head (the ſtomack ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with meat) is very dammage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by alluring humors into the vains.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 3. Excrements of the mouth are to be vacuated by ſpitting, of the lungs by hauking, of the noſtrils by wiping as oft as there is a motion. It is more healthy to eject ſuch ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities by the mouth and noſtrils, than
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:41178:82"/>than to lade the ſtomack with excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gormandiſing: the brain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is much impaired by impure exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations aſcending from unclean ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 4. Urine, Ordure, and Winde, muſt be exonerated at the firſt motion; many by retaining Urine, and other excrements, have been ſeized by dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and mortal diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 5. Wholly abſtain from all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuations by virtue of Phiſick, as <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Vomits, Blood-letting,</hi> unleſs very urgent neceſſity compel you. <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> and <hi>Purges,</hi> as well as they do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel evil humours, exhauſt the good and profitable, yea the Vital Spirits, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by naturall virtue doth decay. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Plato</hi> in <hi>Timeo,</hi> forbad the uſe of <hi>Purgations,</hi> when the cure of the body might be otherwiſe accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 6. To eat twelve Raiſons of the Sunne ſtoned, every morning, without drink, inſtead of breakfaſt, conſerveth <hi>Memory,</hi> comforteth the ſtomack and Liver, diminiſheth Phlegme, augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth blood, and preſerveth youth,</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:41178:83"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 7. Let your Supper be larger then Dinner, becauſe the ſubſequent diſtance of time is longer; but ſuch as are incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with nocturnal diſtillations, (as old men, and cold conſtitutions) muſt eat more plentifully at Dinner then Supper. At meals hot things are to precede before cold; things of eaſie digeſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore things of hard; and liquid things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſolid, for their better concoction in the ſtomack. All ſolid meat requireth long chewing: Drink muſt be ſwallowed leiſurely by degrees: Beware of conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming much time in eating and drinking. Eating too ſlowly is as noxious as eating overfaſt. Conclude your meat with a piece of Bread, Coriander Confects, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melade of Quinces, dryed Pears, or the like. Laſtly, let the quantity of Food be proportionable to the takers ſtrength, not his appetite; for as <hi>Varro</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is one thing to ſuffice a man, another thing to ſuffice humanity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 8. Obſerve conſtant accuſtomed hours of eating: Nature coveteth to perform her office of concoction at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain limited hours, as is manifeſtly ſeen in ſits of intermitting Feavers: Moreover after Supper drink not at all (enſuing
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:41178:83"/>ſleep will moiſten ſufficiently) nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Dinner and Supper, unleſs you be very thirſty, or ſo accuſtomed by long uſe; yet ſuch vicious cuſtoms are to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by degrees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 9. Refrain from labor both of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and mind after meats, ſpend about an hour in delectable diſcourſes with compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſitting, ſtanding or walking gently. Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting near the fire after meat, doth much impede digeſtion, by revocation of the internal heat to the external parts: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe after Supper abſtain as long from ſleep, it being very obſtructive to the brain to ſleep upon a full ſtomack.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 10. At bed-time ſhut all the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of your lodging, that no Winde may enter; and alſo the Window-ſhuts, leaſt <hi>Lunaries</hi> penetrating the Window, moleſt you ſleeping. Sleep under the Moon-beams cauſeth head-ach, though it doth not hurt ſuch as are awake. Let your head and ears be covered; yet too much covering offendeth the head. When you go to bed, firſt lye down on your right ſide, your head onely ſo much ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, as in height may equallize your left ſhoulder, your arms and thighs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what contracted; by ſuch poſition of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:41178:84"/>body, ſtomachical heat is encreaſed: when you are about to ſleep, turn on your left ſide: Again, when you awake, turn on the right ſide, and extend your legs at full length: Let your ſleep be equal to your waking, not in time, but proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, left the brain be too much exſiccated by watching, or moiſtned by ſleeping.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 11. Elect learned men well edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated for Companions and Conſorts, ſuch as near as may be, whoſe converſation may render you better and more learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not ſuch as your ſociety may improve. It is a notable argument we may be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the manners of thoſe with whom we converſe, ſeeing Education among Countrey Clowns, makes men ruſtical; among godly people, makes men pious; thoſe who live with learned men, grow more learned; and they which are educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Families of noble men, ill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are moſt commonly ſcoffers &amp; drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards. So powerful is the cuſtom of thoſe among whom we live, that it is of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er efficacy to form mens manners, then natural inclination it ſelf; you cannot therefore be too curious in choice of your company.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:41178:84"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 12. The mind muſt be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſed in learning ſome ſentences by heart (yea though there be no need) that the faculty of remembring may be quickned by uſe and practice; for as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral vigor is continually augmented by labour and exerciſe, and diminiſhed by ſloth and neglect of labour, ſo the mind accuſtomed to diligent ſtudy of learning, gains ſtrength, by eaſe and idleneſs is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired: As frequent diſputation render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Students skilful Logicians, and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Preaching makes a man an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Orator: So frequent practice of learning by heart, maketh Memory more prompt in operation. There is nothing ſaith <hi>Ludovicus Vives,</hi> doth more delight in pains and labour, then Memory, nor doth ſooner corrupt and periſh by idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; therefore ſomething muſt be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every day (though there be no neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) if it be onely but to prevent ſtupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Memory, which of all Diſeaſes is moſt pernicious to it. Hence theſe two Verſicles aptly repreſent a Rule.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sepe recordari medicamine fortius omni</l>
                  <l>Solus &amp; artificem qui facit, uſus erit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:41178:85"/>
                  <l>Practice of Memory doth more conduce</l>
                  <l>Then Medicine, Skill doth ariſe from uſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 13. The apteſt time for Study, is when the Stomach is empty, then pureſt ſpirits aſcend from the heart to the brain. Hence <hi>Aurora</hi> is eſteemed moſt grateful to the <hi>Muſes;</hi> it is alſo convenient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat every night briefly what you have ſtudied by day, which is reported to have been <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his cuſtom. <hi>It is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful thing, and the reaſon not eaſily percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible</hi> (ſaith <hi>Quintillian</hi>) <hi>how much firmneſs one nights interpoſition doth contribute to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, whether quiet, mature, or concocted;</hi> ſo ſoon as ſleep is ſhaken off, the ſame things are to be rehearſed again, which were meditated before ſleep the evening laſt paſt, otherwiſe nocturnal lucubration doth yeild little benefit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 14 Let no man devote himſelf to a Study or Profeſſion for which he is unapt by Nature; whatſoever Science you adviſedly make choice of, delight therein, employ all diligence in ſtudying the ſame, accounting it greater glory to excel therein, then to be able trivially to diſpute of many other Arts.</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:41178:85"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 15. Addict your ſelf to the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt Maſter in that Profeſſion you have choſen; give attention to him with deep admiration, as to one delivering Oracles; forſake him not till you participate of the profoundeſt myſteries of the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Many would have proved ſingular, had they not eſteemed it a ſhame to be Schollars too long.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 16. Read the choiceſt Authors, ſuch as do not force their Books with trifles: Seeing we cannot be ignorant, that ſtudy exhauſteth the Spirits, we muſt have a care of conſuming them in reading un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Commentaries of illiterate men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 17. Covet not to read many Books, but to underſtand perfectly what you read. It doth not ſo much concern Bodily health, how much we eat, as how well we digeſt what we eat: So deliber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Reading is more advantagious then confuſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 18. Follow the conciſeſt method in ſtudy; for as in going a journey, he which taketh the ſhorteſt and plaineſt way is leſs defatigated at Evening, then he that diverteth to rough or by-wayes; ſo it is in this caſe; the more ſuccinct me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:41178:86"/>we obſerve in learning any Science, the more and ſpeedily we attain the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 19. Apply not your ſelf to ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Study, if you can procure any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in the ſame, at leaſt uſe frequent conference with others, of things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to Diſcipline.</p>
               <p>Mutual Diſcourſe about profitable queſtions, will not onely promote your Studies much, but alſo bring promptneſs of tongue, rendering you more capable to ſpeak publikely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rule</hi> 20. To conclude, if your mind be at any time diſturbed with ſtudy, uſe a little relaxation. It is better ſtudy be intermitted, then the underſtanding over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arcus enim ſi nunquam ceſſes tendere, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus erit,</hi> as ſung the Poet; A bow that is always bent, will ſtubborn grow. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations of the mind onely, are muſick, diſputes with merry facetious perſons; beholding ſolemn ſpectacles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some ſcantling of time muſt be alſo allowed for daily exerciſe of body, but not in the morning, to be ſet a part for more ſolid Studies; rather in the afternoon, or a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before Supper, that the heat extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:41178:86"/>externally, may have recourſe before you take refection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of reſtoring a debilitated Memory.</head>
               <p>HAving premiſed Rules for conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Natural Memory in good eſtate, I will next preſcribe ſome helps for the ſame debilitated.</p>
               <p>Imbecillity of Natural Memory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from too much heat, coldneſs; moiſture, or dryneſs of the brain. Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much heat waſteth and conſumeth ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſpirits; too much coldneſs obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth motion of the Spirits lodged in the Cells of the Brain; ſuperfluous dryneſs cauſeth ſuch callocity, that the ſpecies cannot be imprinted: Redundant moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture doth eraſe and obliterate forms of things, as ſoon as they are imprinted. If there happen exceſs in two qualityes (as if the Brain be hot and moiſt, cold and moiſt, hot and dry, or cold and dry) the Brain, and conſequently memory is more infeſted. Therefore the whole buſineſs of curing debilitated memory, conſiſteth in
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41178:87"/>augmentation or diminution of callidity and humidity of brain.</p>
               <p>Weakneſs of memory ariſeth from ſome ſmall indiſpoſition or Diſeaſe; if it be onely indiſpoſed through bad dyet or diſordered courſe of life, thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are to be obſerved which are aſſigned particularly to every man, according to his conſtitution in the ſixt Chapter, not neglecting the general dyet before preſcribed, and common rules of living delivered in the former Chapter, ſo far as is found agreeable to each mans Temperament.</p>
               <p>That a man may better judge of his brains temperament, I have thought neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary briefly to enumerate the ſigns of the brains temperament, collected out of the works of learned Phyſicians. Although the temperaments of the brain as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of quality, are almoſt innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet they are reduced to nine more general, the ſigns of which I will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in few words.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:41178:87"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How to diſcern the temperament of the BRAIN.</head>
               <p>IN the firſt place take the ſignes of a temperate Brain, which are theſe: The poſſeſſors thereof are not offended with heat, cold, moiſture, or drineſs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from external cauſes; they alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy intire ſences, moſt apt to learn all Diſcipline and good Arts, nor are they haſtily precipitated into paſſions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of mind; their dreams are few and pleaſant, ſometimes they dream of flying, becauſe their bodies, incumbred with no excrements, ſeem indued with very great levity and agility; ſometimes they dream of Stars, and ſuch like ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did things, the colour of ſuch perſons hair (if they live in temperate Regions) whiles they are children, is yellowiſh; when they are men, a deep yellow; then alſo the hair of their heads becomes curl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in age they wax hoary ſlowly, and are ſeldom bald. To conclude, they are moderate in all things, both in animal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, (as pulſe, reſpiration, ſleep, &amp;c.)
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41178:88"/>and in redundancies, as Excrements of the Ears, Noſe, Mouth, and ſuperfluities of other parts, all which in quantity and quality are found to be in mediocrity.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Signs of a hot Brain. When heat predominates, the Head is hot in feeling, the parts about the head are hot and rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the eyes are red and quick in motion, the veins conſpicuous, hair begins togrow upon the head preſently after Nativity, and encreaſe apace; ſuch as far exceed temperate perſons in heat, have black curled hair on their heads, which in age doth ſhed, and cauſe baldneſs: Superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their pallats, noſtrils, eyes and ears are few, their ſleep is ſhort, and not deep; their heads are offended with hot meats, potions and odours, ſo much the more if theſe things be naturally hot: Pulſe and Reſpiration is quicker then in perſons poſſeſſed of a temperate Brain; they excel in memory, are agile in their actions, prone to wrath and venery, and enjoy perfect ſences.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Signs of a cold Brain. If coldneſs predominate, the Head is cold in touch, ſcarcely any red doth appear in the face, and that in cold ſeaſons converted to a bleak blewiſh hue, their eyes are weak,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:41178:88"/>their veins inconſpicuous, their Pulſe and Reſpiration more ſlow then in temperate perſons, their hair grows not till ſome ſpace after birth, thin, ſmooth, not ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and turning hoary, without bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; their head is ſeldom hurt by hot, but facilely offended by cold cauſes, whence proceeds frequent diſtillations, rheums, ſtoppings, ſtuffings and pozes of the Noſtrils; they are ſleepy, timorous, ſlow to anger, leſs deſirous of Venery; their memory is treacherous, mind ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, and ſences weak, eſpecially their hearing; ſubject alſo to ſwimmings of the Head, called <hi>Vertigo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. Signs of a moiſt brain. In ſuch in whom moiſture doth abound, the head-hair is plain and copious, plenty of hair proceeding from moiſture, as colour doth from heat, for which cauſe moiſt brains never wax bald; their hair alſo ſeemeth bedewed with an airy oily fat humour, if it ariſe from natural humidity of the brain, or elſe with a wateriſh thin hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, if procured by preternatural hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity of Brain: Moreover ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have dull wits, are ſlow in motion, retain faithfully in memory things late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſt, but forget things acted long ſince;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:41178:89"/>their ſence of ſmelling is weak, their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſences imperfect; they abound with Excrements expelled by the noſe, mouth, eyes, &amp;c. their ſleep is long and deep; they dream ſometimes they are in jeopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and unable to move themſelves from the place, becauſe bodies laden with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities are made ſluggiſh.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Signs of a dry Brain. Dry Brains learn ſlowly, and do not eaſily forget; ſuperfluities of Noſtrils, Eyes and Palate are few, but Ear-was much; their Eyes are hollow, the hair of their heads hard and curled, growing ſpeedily bald.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Signs of a hot and moiſt Brain. Such as partake of hot and moiſt brains, have hot heads, humours alſo find paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through the ſutures of the Scull, they have a good colour in their faces, their eye-veins are conſpicuous, head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair copious, ſtreight and yellowiſh; their ſences ſomewhat dull, ſoon grow bald, prone to Venery, quicker in motion then temperate people, propenſe to anger, yet not cruel; cannot watch much, yet are they vigilant, oft ſee obſcure Viſions in Dreams, their Excrements arc copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:41178:89"/> VII. Signs of a hot dry Brain. They which are poſſeſſed of a hot dry Brain, are ſlender of Body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet their joynts and muſcles firmly knit together; they have great Veins, perfect Sences, compleat nimble motion, a ſtrong loud ſounding Voice, hard brown Skins, their Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair grows ſpeedily, being black and curl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ſheds ſpeedily; their bodies are very hairy, they excel in wit and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, are inconſtant in their Opinions; their ſleep is light and ſhort, dreaming moſt commonly of fiery things; they are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle eaters, have few excrements, and are audacious, proud, liberal, temeracious, and prone to Venery.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. Signs of a cold moiſt brain. Such as are indued with cold humid brains, have dull ſences, weak pulſe, ſlow motion, heads repleniſhed with ſuperfluities, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them obnoxious to Rhumes and Poſes; their ſleep is much, great and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found; they dream of water and watery meteors, as ſnow, rain, hail, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeldom become bald, are not long angry; finally, they abound with ſuperfluous humours.</p>
               <p n="19">XIX. Signs of a cold dry Brain. Such as partake of a cold dry brain, enjoy ſound intire ſences in youth, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:41178:90"/>begin to decline, they ſoon grow old and hoary; the Veins of their Eyes are inconſpicuous, little annoyed with excrements, but eaſily prejudiced by cold cauſes; they often dream of ſmoake, myſts and great darkneſs: If cold pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominate over dryneſs, they grow bald more ſlowly; if dryneſs exceed cold, more ſpeedily; Reſpiration and Pulſe is more ſlow and rare, they participate of ſmall quantity of Blood; have ſomewhat hard bodies; to conclude, they are not quickly pacified being angry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Dyet properly convenient to every temperament.</head>
               <p>HAving expoſed to your view the ſigns of the Brain's temperament, Order requires I ſhould in the next place ſpecifie a particular Dyet for every tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament, onely omitting the firſt kind, compounded of an equal Commixtion of the four qualities for whoſoever is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of ſuch a temperament of Brain, or nearly related thereto, enjoyeth a good memory, and therefore needeth no
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:41178:90"/>Phyſical Precepts; the chief buſineſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on ſuch a bleſſed Eſtate, is to preſerve it, by ſhunning all things perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the memorative faculty, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe profitable things before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
               <p n="2">II. If the Brain ſuffer through exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive heat, endeavour muſt be uſed to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the ſame; perſons ſo infeſted muſt abſtain from all things augmenting or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing heat; ſuch are moſt Aromatical Spices, as, <hi>Pepper, Ginger, Cloves,</hi> &amp;c. All ſorts of Wine and ſtrong Drink; Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, &amp;c. violent exerciſes muſt be eſchu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hot Solar beams, eſpecially at noon and after meat, as alſo ſtudy after Supper, let ſuch perſons eat cold ſowr fruits after meals, ſmell often to things of a cold ſcent, as are Violets, Roſes, Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, natural Camphire, Roſe-water, Wood-bine Flowers, Mullein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create their Spirits ſometimes in Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, where Flowers and odoriferous Herbs breath a fragrant ſmell, walking in the ſhade: So ſoon as they are ready in a morning, let them waſh their faces in cold water, dipping their eyes open therein, that the water may ſoak and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frigate their eyes; in like manner at E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:41178:91"/>towards Bed-time, let them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint their temples, and two uppermoſt Spondyle, with Oyle of Roſes, which doth diminiſh the heat of the Brain, and alſo procure Ileep, which hot brains want not a little.</p>
               <p n="3">III. If the Brain be over-cold, it muſt be tempered by abſtinence from things of a refrigerative nature, and uſe of hot things; perſons afflicted with a cold Brain, muſt deſiſt from uſing all things which cool the Brain, as Lettice, Musk-Melons, Brown-bread, Brains of living Creatures that are humide, as of Calves, Pigs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unripe fruits, green herbs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boiled water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let them decline the Moon and Northerly Winds, eat hot vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, uſe theſe Aromatical Spices, being very profitable, Pepper, Cloves, Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Mace, Nutmegs, Ginger, Juniper-Berries, Ivory-ſhavings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hot Odours comfort the Brain, exhaled from Balm, <hi>Mint,</hi> Galangal, Roſemary, Lignum Aloes, Oranges, Amber, Musk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Moreover Green Ginger eaten faſting twice or thrice a Week, in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a ſmall Nut, doth much commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date a cold Brain. Likewiſe Wine of good colour, taſte, and Odour taken
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:41178:91"/>moderately. It is expedient once a month to waſh the hinder part of the head and neck toward bed time, with hot water, wherein <hi>Balme, Cammomile, Sage, Bay-leaves, Hyſſope, Fennel, Sweet-Marjerome,</hi> &amp;c. have been decocted; Laſtly, Unction of the nape of the neck, and two uppermoſt ſpondyles with tepid oyl of <hi>Dill</hi> or <hi>Rue,</hi> admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth great benefit to a cold <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If the brain abound with ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humors, care muſt be taken to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them, and reduce the brain to its due temper. Let moiſt brains therefore abſtain from all humid and Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick things, as <hi>Broths, Pottage, Milk, Swines fleſh,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Pigge,</hi> young <hi>Lanbs, Chickens</hi> before they are plumed, <hi>Musk-Melons,</hi> &amp;c. Let them refrain from uſe of <hi>Garlick, Onions, Strong Drinks,</hi> and all other things which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſh the brain with groſs Vapors; and be carefull their food be free from all <hi>viſcoſity,</hi> leſt through augmentation of Phlegmatical matter in the brain by fly mie meat, they render themſelves obnoxious to <hi>Apoplexies, Lethargies,</hi> or <hi>Palſies.</hi> Let their meat be well ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:41178:92"/>with ſalt, for that doth very much exiccate and cut Phlegmatick hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and rarifies the Spirits, being beſt of all ſauces for moiſt brains. Let them ſhun Southern winds, and all things repleniſhing the head with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors. Chewing of Maſtick with Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Pellitory of <hi>Spain,</hi> doth migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily purge the head of Phlegmatick ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities; the ſame effect is procured by Sage held ſome ſpace in the mouth: it is alſo ſalutiferous to ſwallow a grain of the pureſt white Frankincenſe. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco (ſo called from the Iſle <hi>Tobacque</hi>) temperately taken, is beneficial<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for moiſt brains, chiefly when the head is repleat with more then uſual ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities, but too frequent uſe thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes Radical moiſture, augmenting Rhumes and diſtillations by accident; for as a Well (the more it is exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with buckets) doth more abound with water, ſo the head frequently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuated by ſmoke of Tobacco, is dayly repleniſhed with greater abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of humors. Juyce of <hi>Citrons</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken faſting is much more excellent to digeſt Phlegmatick matter, then To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, which I think, no man that
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:41178:92"/>makes experience will deny.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the brain be too dry, it muſt be lenified with moiſtners, ſuch people muſt abſtain from ſalt meats, and all drying things, and avoid the eaſt wind, Let them eat moiſt and ſucculent things, as Rear Eggs, Capons, Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, Mountain Birds, Kidds fleſh, new Cheeſe unſalted, freſh water fiſh caught in gravelly places, Milk, Broth, Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Prunes, Pomegranats, Figgs, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, Succory, Endive, Lettice, and like things, ſmall drink, if they drink wine at any time, let it be allayed with water, and eſchew all violent motion; if their bodies be coſtive, let them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe cooling moiſtening Clyſters, than Purgations.</p>
               <p>So much for the four ſimple quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties annoying the Brain, which things well obſerved, I may be more brief in the other four temperaments, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of theſe compounded; for if the Brain be infeſted with two peccant qualities, as too hot and moiſt, or two hot and dry, in ſuch compound tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments, ſuch things as we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to mittigate either quality, are to be uſed, ſo far as one doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:41178:93"/>the alteration of another. If of two qualities, one is more predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant than the other, and more affect the Brain, we muſt proportionally more oppoſe the ſtronger; but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our purpoſe, and ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of compound temperaments, as well as of ſimple.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He which hath a Brain too hot and moiſt, muſt fly all moiſtening and heating things, refreſhing himſelf with cold and dry things; for ſuch the North wind is good, the South wind hurtfull: cold dry odours are moſt fit for them, as <hi>Saunders, Roſewood, Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Lotions</hi> made of cooling drying herbs decocted; unctions with cooling drying oyls, as oyl of <hi>Myrtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries,</hi> of <hi>Cammomil flowers,</hi> oyl of <hi>Hony,</hi> oyl of <hi>Roſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Brains hot and dry in exceſs, muſt decline hot and dry things, and recover themſelves with cooling moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, avoiding the Eaſt wind: Let them be moſt commonly bare headed, and chooſe their habitations (if they may) in a cold moiſt Region, near ſome river; let their lodging-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be a low room, paved with Tyles.
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:41178:93"/>Towards ſleep let them anoynt their heads with oyl of <hi>Violets,</hi> or of <hi>Water-Lillies,;</hi> cold moiſt ſcents are moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious for them, as of <hi>Mullein, Nightſhade, Roſes, Violets, Water-Lillies, Willow leaves,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Perſons afflicted with brains too cold and moiſt, (to which diſtemper moſt Students are incident) have a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak <hi>Memorative faculty,</hi> for of the four primary qualities, <hi>Humidity</hi> and <hi>Frigidity,</hi> are moſt noxious to <hi>Memory,</hi> but <hi>Frigidity</hi> moſt of all; yet the Brain is more facilely and ſpeedily cured of theſe diſtempers, than of the others, becauſe the Brain (of the ſeven prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Members) is naturally moiſt, cold, and humid, ſo that hot and dry things applyed to qualifie its intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateneſs, are leſs dangerous. To thoſe things which are ſeverally delivered before for help of cold moiſt Brains, theſe things may be added, all hot and dry things, as <hi>Aromatical ſpices,</hi> Nutmegs Ginger, Cynnamon Powder of Euphorbium, Zedoarie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of Herbs, Balme, Marjerome, Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſſes, Hyſope, Tyme, Piony, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In Conſerves. Of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:41178:94"/>Food, Sparrows, Partridges, Turtles, Larkes, Pheaſants, Capons, Weather-Mutton, and Goats-fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sack drunk temperately. Alſo Conval Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies diſtilled with ſtrong wine, the quantity of a ſpoonfull drunk, is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular againſt all infirmities of head or Brain, proceeding from a Frigid or humid cauſe, doth Vivifie the <hi>Memory</hi> and <hi>Sences,</hi> and exhilerate the heart: Conſerve of Roſemary flowers is of like virtue. After meat it is good to eat Conſerve of Quinces, Anniſeeds, or Cynnamon in Confects, or Corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeeds boyled in vinegar, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Confected. Heating drying O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours yield much comfort, ſuch as is exhaled from <hi>Lignum Aloes, Styrax, Muske, Civet, Ladanum, Bettony, Nigella, Roſemary, Lavander,</hi> &amp;c. It is alſo very profitable to anoynt the Temples once a moneth with <hi>Partridges Gall,</hi> till it penetrate. <hi>Frication</hi> of the head in a morning faſting with courſe clothes perfumed with <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> as alſo much and frequent Exerciſe, is very beneficial. Moiſt humours may be ſometimes expelled from the head by <hi>ſneeſing powders,</hi> amongſt which <hi>Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs</hi>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:41178:94"/>challenge the firſt place; <hi>Bettony</hi> rubbed to powder, and ſnuffed up into the Noſtrils, provoketh ſneeſing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any offence, but is onely to be uſed the ſtomake being empty. Oyl of <hi>Tyles,</hi> or <hi>Oleum Philoſophorum</hi> (as ſome call it) tepified, and anoynted on the hinder part of the head, and uppermoſt rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bones, doth wonderfully reſtore <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> decayed by a cold or humid cauſe. To conclude, all cold moiſt food and ſauces, are hurtfull, no leſſe noxious is moiſt air, and cold morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, evening, or Nocturnul ſeaſons, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to lie out all night in the open air.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Such as are oppreſſed with too much coldneſſe and dryneſs of Brain (to which qualities moſt aged men are ſubjected) muſt eat frequently a little at a time, nouriſhing themſelves with <hi>humective</hi> dyet, ſuch as heateth mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, as <hi>Rear Eggs, New butter, ſweet Almonds, Filbirds, Pine-apple-kernels, Cheſnuts, Piſtachioes.</hi> All nouriſhing meats, and ſweet things, as <hi>Lyquorice, Hony, Sugar, Raiſins, Conſerves</hi> of <hi>Borage</hi> and <hi>Bugloſſe, Cytron peel Preſerved.</hi> Strong ſweet wine, as <hi>Muſkadine, Ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras,</hi>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:41178:95"/>drunk temporately is moſt reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative for old folks, and cold and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons, more efficaciouſly Gold (made almoſt red hot in the fire) quenched therein, doth marvellouſly reſtore and exhilerace the heart. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter, <hi>Roger Bacon,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Philoſopher, in his Treatiſe of old age, hath this ſtory; <hi>An ancient husbandman</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wearyed with plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and thirſty with his hot labour, drank water of a Cytron colour, and after he had greedily ſwallowed the ſame, was changed both in complection and ſtrength like one of thirty years of age, poſſeſſing more excellent diſcretion, memory and underſtanding, than ever he enjoyed before, from which time he lived eighty years in the Kings Court, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> who reciteth this thought, that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or liquor received its yellow Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture from Gold, as he there teſtifieth. Moreover to anoynt the hinde part of the head, neck, ſtomake, belly, feet, (and other parts of the body, if you pleaſe) with <hi>Oyl of Lillies or Cammomil,</hi> is very beneficial. The anſwer of <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio</hi> doth notably inſtruct us how profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Oyl</hi> are to conſerve
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:41178:95"/>health, who having attained to the age of an hundred years, and asked by the Emperour <hi>Auguſtus</hi> (as <hi>Pliny</hi> relateth) <hi>by what means he had preſerved vigour both of minde and body to that age?</hi> replyed, <hi>By wine within, and oyl without.</hi> Baths made of Decoctions of hot and moiſt hearbs are moſt uſefull, as alſo hot Odours, but all things moiſt and cold are to be avoided. The conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt time of Studie for old men, is when their brain is moderately warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with wine, or meats of good nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment; then the <hi>Idea's</hi> of Notions do as it were bubble and erect themſelves, whereby Invention is exacuated; for <hi>Phantaſie</hi> pertaking of corporeal quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is excited by meat and Drink. It is uſually ſeen at firſt fitting down of Gueſts to a banquet, deep ſilence oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieth them all, but after their brains are tepified with Spirits of Wine and good meat, their Fancies are elevated, and all the company begins to prate.</p>
               <p>This may ſuffice for recovery of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitated <hi>Memories,</hi> when no diſeaſe is contracted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:41178:96"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of Diſeaſes of the Brain.</head>
               <p>IF <hi>Memory</hi> be ſo far impaired, ſome diſeaſe enſueth, recourſe muſt be had to Phyſick as to the laſt refuge, wherein nothing is to be undertaken without a Phyſitians advice; for though there be many medicines found in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Authors, whereby a very much decayed and languiſhing <hi>Memory</hi> may be reſtored, yet it is unſafe to rely wholly upon ſuch written directions: ſo long as <hi>Memory</hi> doth proſperouſly diſcharge its Office, according to the innate temperament of the Brain; yea though declining ſomewhat from tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateneſſe, there muſt be a totall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence from Phyſick, becauſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture often accuſtomed to Phyſicall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, will alwaies expect them, when interrupted, and ſo become remiſſe in undergoing its charge ſo true is that common <hi>Proverb,</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:41178:96"/>
               <p> Natura ſonos fruſtra medicina fatigat.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>In health, they do abuſe</l>
                  <l>Nature, who Phyſick uſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But now it is high time to contract ſails, and put this work into a Harbor, concluding with <hi>Horace,</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Vive, vale ſi quid noviſti rectius iſtis,</l>
                  <l>Candidus imperti; ſi non, his utere me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
